foreign
[Music]
In this video we will discus delta hedging.
We will start with obtaining expression
for dXt using Ito's lemma.
Then we will give the formula for dXt using replicating strategy idea.
And, finally, we will obtain a simple
receipt for replication strategy.
Okay, the price of a claim XT is a function
of share prices T and time T. So, Xt is
some function X of St and t. Why it is so?
Because we have some replicating
strategy. And, so, to replicate our
financial claim, we need to make some initial investment.
And the initial investments, we will do
them in the shares and in bonds. So, but
the bond price is a function of T. It's
non-stochastic. The share price St is
known. So, we know how much to invest to
start replicating strategy. And, basically,
Xt should depend only on St and T. We
don't know the formula. We know it, but it
cannot depend on some additional terms.
Using it as layer month, we obtain
expression for dXt. It's a first
derivative with respect to T times Dt
plus the first derivative with respect
to S times times Ds plus Ito's correction term 1 over 2 times the,
second derivative Dx with respect to
DS, DS times Ds squared.
But from as a viewpoint we know, that the
final answer will simplify somehow, I
don't know how yet. It will simplify up
to something times DT plus something
times dWt. I don't care, basically, about
the term before Dt, I will focus on the
term before dWt.
Let's do this.
Once again, we have an expression using Ito's lemma,
and we know the structure of the answer,
that is Dx, dXt equals to something times
Dt plus something times dWt.
There are no dWt in dSt square root,
because according to
mnemonic rules, Dt times Dt is 0, Dt
times dWtt is 0, and Dt dWt times dWt is
Dt. When you square dSt, you cannot get
dWt. Okay, so, only in dSt we have dWt, more
exactly, dSt is sigma times St times dWt.
Okay, so, the shorthand notation for dXt is something times Dt,
I don't care about this term times this
term, I care about. Dx times Ds times
sigma St times dWt.
Okay, let's calculate dXt the other way.
Let's use the replicating portfolio idea.
Imagine, we have Yt shares and Zt bonds
in our portfolio. So, the price of
portfolio Xt is Yt times s t plus ZT
times BT. That's just the balance.
Okay, but the interpretation of
stochastic integral is a net cash flow.
So, Xt is equal to X0 plus integral from
0 to tYu times dSu. So, that's a
net flow from shares plus integral
from 0 to T times Zu times gBu, that is
the cash flow from bonds. And my strategy
is self-financing. My portfolio is self
financing. So, these two flows should
compensate each other.
Or in short form dXt is YT times dSt
plus ZT times DBT.
Once again, we need to recap the idea,
that's stochastic integral represents
the net cash flow.
And in Black and Scholes model we know, that
DsT is Mu StDt, I don't care about this
term plus. That's important sigma St
times dWt, and dBt is non-stochastic at
all, dBt is Bt times Dt.
Okay, so, if I focus on dWt term once again.
I just have the same equations. And let's focus on
the term before dWt.
Here it's just Yt times sigma St
times dWt.
Bingo!
We have an informal theorem to replicate
a European type claim with price X of St,
and t we should hold YT shares, and ZT
bonds, where YT is just DX with respect
to DS. So, the number of shares, we need to
have in our portfolio, is the derivative
of the portfolio price with respect to the share price.
That's called the delta hedging rule.
And we all obviously can find out the
number of bonds. The total price of
portfolio is Xt. We have Yt shares. So, Xt
minus total price of shares Xt minus
YtSt the total price of all bonds. We
divide by the price of one bond by BT.
And we get, that T is the number of bonds.
Okay, so, that's a very simple rule, that
gives you explicit receipt, how to
replicate any European type claim.
Obviously, you need to have the formula X
of St and t, but we have the pricing
formula. So, Bingo! We have the pricing
formula for for every European type
asset. And we have a rule how to
replicate every European type asset.
Let's proceed to the summary.
We have obtained two expressions for the
evolution of price of any financial
claim. It's dXt is equal to something
times Dt plus Dx, Dx over Ds times sigma
times sTdwt. The other expression for the
evolution of the price of any financial
claim is dXt equals to something times
Dt plus Yt times sigma times St times
dWt.
These expressions before dWt equal. So,
we have the delta hedging rule: that to
replicate any financial claim, we need to
have in our portfolio Yt shares, where Yt
is the derivative of the portfolio price,
Dx with respect  to the share price Ds
at that moment of time.
That was the last video in our short
introduction. It was rather hard from the
mathematical viewpoint, but let me thank you.
[Music]