[Music]
Stochastic intergrals play important role in the Black
and Scholes model. So, let's calculate our
two first stochastic integrals.
Okay, so, what  is the meaning,
intuitive meaning of stochastic integral?
we treat this quantity,
as the profit of an investor, who has XU
shares, and the price of a share is WU.
Now we have this, let's call it Financial
strategy,
I'm not speaking about its optimality
let's just consider it as given. so we
have a
full trading points. let's draw them on
timeline.
we have starting moment zero. we have a
jump at moment one, so there will be a
transaction at moment one. there will be
also a transaction at moment four and
the final moment of time is five we will
sell our portfolio.
okay at time moment zero,
we should have three shares. so we should
buy that is our first
transaction. we should buy three shares
and the price is w0.
okay at time Moment One
we already have three shares but
according to our strategy we should have
from point one to point four we should
have W1 Square shares. so so we we should
additionally Buy
W1 squared minus three. we already
have three shares. so We additionally buy
the quantity we would like to have minus
the quantity we already have shares.
Given,
that the price is  W1
at that moment four,
we have one more  transaction, we
additionally buy. Let's calculate, how
many before time moment four we have W1
squared, shares after moment four, we
should have W two square root shares, so,
we additionally buy W2 square root minus
W1 squared shares,
and their price is W4.
And, finally, we sell everything at time
moment five, we sell the portfolio, we
have.
So, we sell W2 square shares,
and the price of each share is W5. Okay,
let's calculate our profit, and this
profit will be the value of our
stochastic integral. So, let's write
all, we should spend with minus, and all
we should receive is plus, that's
basically the value of an integral. So, we
get minus three times W0 quantity times
price minus W1 square root minus three
times W1
minus W2 minus W1 squared times W4,
and here we sell. So, we receive money, we
get plus W2 squared times W5, so, that's
the value of our stochastic integral.
Once again, I'm not pretending, that we
are actually buying, maybe, this quantity
is negative, so, we are selling in
this case, and, hence,  this value will
be  with plus, but that's completely
okay. This formula will take care of,
whether we buy, whether we sell, so, that's
a final result.
Okay, and what about the other integral?
Let's consider it  in more details
integral from 0 to 5, to WU plus three
dWu.
In this case we are doing transaction at
every moment of time.
So, we're doing transaction infinitely
many times, and we should consider some
limiting, some sense,
if we are doing rigorous mass, but we
will just use a table of integrals and
the properties of stochastic integrals.
They are linear, so, we get two
integrals from zero to five W dWu plus
integral from 0 to 5 3dWu.
And, basically, this integral is in our
table. So, we will get 2 times
W5 squared minus
five
over two
plus. And this one we may calculate it in
intuitively, we should buy at the initial
moment of time three shares, and we will
sell them at the final moment of time. So,
we should buy minus 3 times W0, and we
should sell them at the final moment of
time, so, we will get three the number of
shares, times the share price W5.
So, this is the value of our second
stochastic integral.
[Music]