[Music]
In this video we will introduce the main tool to work
with stochastic integrals - the Ito's lemma.
We will start with a light version for
functions of time and Wiener process.
Then we will discuss, how to use Ito's lemma
to check, whether their processes in
martingale.
And then we will introduce a more
general version of Ito's lemma.
So, let's start.
If YT is a function of WT and T, then it
may be written in the form of a Ito
process. So, YT equals to Y0 plus
ordinary integral from 0 to T of F prime
with respect to T plus 1 over 2,
second derivative of F with respect to W
W times DU plus Ito integral from 0 to
TF Prime with respect to W times dWu.
Or we may write the same theorem in the
short form. In the short form the theorem
says, that if YT is a function of WT and
T, then it may be written in the short
form as dYt equals to F prime
with respect to W times dWt plus F prime
with respect to T times DT plus 1 over 2
times second derivative F prime prime
with respect to WW times DT.
Let's get used to this lemma, because
it's not that intuitive.
Let's express the process YT equal to WT
cubed times T power 4, as an Ito process.
Okay, let's calculate dYt.
First, derivatives are 3Wt squared
times T power 4 and we multiply it by
dWt. And the first derivative with
respect to T is 4Wt cubed times T
cubed, we multiply it by DT. And we add
a second derivative with respect to WW, so
it will be 6 WT times T power 4, but we
divide it by 2 according to the it is
Lemma. We simplify this expression,
and, finally, we get the full form, that YT
equals to 0, Y0, we plug in 0 instead of
T,
plus
Ito integral from 0 to T 3WU squared U
power 4 times dWu plus ordinary integral
from 0 to T for WU cubed times U cubed
plus 3 WU times U power 4 times DU.
Okay, how we may use it? Let's check,
whether the process YT equals to
WT power 4 minus T squared is a
martingale.
We will calculate dYt by the same
lemma.
We take first derivatives with respect
to WT and T, we add 1 over 2 times the
second derivative with respect to WW. So,
it will be plus 1 over 2 times 12 WT
squared.
We simplify, we get 4 WT cubed times dWt
plus 6 WT squared minus 2T times DT.
And, hence, in the full form YT is a sum
of 0 plus Ito integral plus three mill
integral. Oh, it has Riemann integral
inside, so, it's not a martingale.
That's very easy. We don't need to
calculate conditional expected value at
all to check, whether the process is a
martingale. We calculate the short form
dYt using Ito's lemma. If it contains  the
the term with DT, it's not a martingale,
if the term with DT disappears, then
our process YT is a martingale.
One more exercise: let's express Yt
equal to WT squared as an Ito process.
And let's prove the formula for an
integral from 0 to T of WU times dWu.
We calculate dYt, using Ito's lemma, so, it
will be 2 WT times DWT plus 0 times DT,
plus the second derivative 1 over 2
times 2 times DT. We simplify it, and we
get 2 WT times DWT plus DT.
We recover the full form, YT is equal to
0 Y 0, I plug 0 instead of TW 0 squared
is zero, so, it's 0 plus Ito integral from
0 to T to WU times dWu plus original
integral from 0 to T of 1 times DU. But
this last integral is very easy, it's
just T.
And, hence, I get the expression for
integral from 0 to T of WU times dWu, it
will be equal one over two times WT
squared minus T, as in our tables.
And we have a more  general version of
it is lemma. If YT is a function of XT
and t, where XT, as an E to process,
then YT may be written in the short form,
as dYt is f prime with respect to X
times DX plus F prime with respect to T
times DT plus 102 times second
derivative with respect to X
times dXt squared.
And to calculate dXt, we use symbolic
rules. DT times DWT is 0. DT times DT is 0,
DWT times DWT is DT. Once again,
these objects like DWT or dYt, or dXt,
they have no meaning, no rigorous
mathematical meaning. This is just a
short form to write less to save time.
And when you write the short form, you
can recover the correct full form.
Let's consider an example.
We know, that DST, the
share price in the framework of Black
and Shcoles model
is given by M times M times ST times
DT plus sigma times ST times DWT. And
let's imagine, that YT is a square of ST.
So, the share price squared. Let's
calculate dYt, and let's recover the full
form for YT.
We use  the second version of Ito's lemma.
dYt is the first derivative with
respect to S. So, it will be
2 ST times DST plus
the first derivative with respect to T.
There are no T. So, it will be 0 times
DT plus we add 1 over 2 times the second
derivative with respect to ST, so, it will
be 2 times we multiply by DST squared.
We open the brackets instead of DST, we
plug in the original expression MST
DT plus sigma STDWT.
Now we open the square,
but DT times DT will replace by zero. DT
times DWT will replace by zero, when we
calculate a square.
And the only remaining term will be
sigma ST times  DWT
times DWT. But DWT times dWT is DT. And,
hence, we rearrange our terms and get the
final expression 2 MST squared plus
sigma squared ST squared times DT plus
2 sigma ST squared times dWt.
And we recover the full form: YT or ST
squared is equal to S0 squared plus
stochastic integral from 0 to T to sigma
SU squared times dWu plus ordinary
integral from 0 to T to MSU squared
plus sigma squared SU squared times DU.
There is an easy way to memorize Ito's lemma.
If you have a function YT of XT
ZTT, where XT and ZT are Ito
processes, then the short form of YT may
be obtained in two steps. First calculate
the second order taylor expansion of
this function F and then simplify the
result using symbolic rules DT times dYt.
DWT is 0, DT times DT is zero, DWT times
DWT is DT.
And this process will give the correct a
full form, if you will replace the short
form by the corresponding full form.
And, once again, we should remember, that
dWt, dYt, dXt, dZt
this is just a convention to simplify
notation. They do not exist. They are not
random variables. It's impossible to
calculate the expected value of DWT. It's
impossible to calculate its variance. It is
just a quick way, an easy way to write the steps necessary to obtain the full form.
And let's proceed to the summary.
It is lemma is a basic tool to study
stochastic integrals. One may use, for
example, it is lamb to check, whether a
given process in continuous time is a
martingale.
The Ito's lemma is easily memorized in a
short form, using symbolic rules DT times
DWT is 0, DT times DT is 0, DWT times DWT
is DT.
[Music]