[Music]
The Black and Scholes model assumes no arbitrage pricing. So,
let's solve some non-arbitrage pricing problem.
Imagine a market, when we have the risk-free rate
is equal to 0 0 or 5 1 3,
the price of a share at time zero is 7.
And we are interested in a call option
price. We strike price K equal to zero.
And we have two more assets, that are traded  in our market.
So, for 0.8 we can buy a very interesting
contract, that will pay us
one dollar, if S2, the share price at
moment 2, will be less than zero. And we
have another strange contract. We can buy for
current price three dollars. We can buy a
contract, that will give us one share, but
only if the share price at moment 2
will be less than 10.
Okay, we have a market, and we need to
price a call option.
First, let's fill this table with more
information. Okay, if I'd like just to
have one share at time T equal to 2 unconditionally.
Then, obviously, I can just buy it now,
put it in a box and wait two years
and, oh, I have one share. So, this
simple contract can be simulated with
one share. So, its price is just seven.
If I'd like to have  just one dollar
unconditionally at time moment two, how
can I simulate this contract? Oh, I
need to put some amount of money on a bank account,
but they're risk-free, interest rate is
0 0 5 1 3. Okay, so,
the current price of one dollar now
is exponent of minus 2 times R
times one dollar. And if I will calculate
this exponent of minus 2 times 0 0 5 1 3
times 1 dollar or two years later, I will
get roughly 0 9. Okay, so, to get one dollar,
I need to pay now zero nine dollars.
Now what is a call option?  What is a call option?
I don't know its price, yeah, it's some
C0 I'm searching for. Yeah, that is
C0 they call option price,
but the call option price has this structure of payments.
If S2 is less, than 10 then call option
price or call option is the right to buy
a share, so, basically, if S2 is less
than zero, this call option is useless
and its price is zero. But if S2 is
greater or equal than 10, then call
option price is in the money.
And its price is given by
S2 minus strike price, strike price is 10,
so, S2 minus 10.
Okay, and let's exploit the non-arbitrage
condition for these five,
basically, we have five assets.
I will replicate my option,
my call option using four other
assets. So, I will use replication
strategy. Oka,y let's add weights a b
small C, that is not a call option price,
that is just small C and small D. I will
invest A, B, C, D, I will buy a assets
of the first type B, assets of the second
type C, assets of this third type and so
on. And I would like to recover this payoff structure.
Okay, let's do it.
Let's work with our simulated asset.
What is the current price of this replication.
We have a times 0 8 plus b times 3, plus
c times 7, plus d times 0 9. Okay, and
what is the future payoff structure of
this combination?
The future payoff structure of this
combination is the following:
if S2 is less than 10, which one will work?
If S2 is less than 10, I will receive this
dollar, I will receive this share, I
will receive this and I will receive
that, because the third and the force are
unconditional. Okay, so, I will get a plus d plus S2 times b plus c.
What happens, if S2 is greater or equal
than 10? One I will get.
I will get unconditional assets, and that's all. So, basically, if S2
is greater than 10, I will get only D
plus S2 times C.
And I need to replicate my call option.
Okay, so, it's easy to replicate: I just
need to set a plus, D should be zero,
B plus C should be zero, D should be equal to -10,
and C should be equal to 1. I have a
very big system of four linear equations.
That's easy to solve them.
A is 10 and B is minus one.
So, a is 10.
B is -1.
C is one.
and D is -10.
And if I buy 10 first type assets, I
sell one second type asset, I buy one
type asset, and I sell minus, I sell
10 force type asset.Okay, so, the C0 should be
10 times 0 8, minus 1 times 3, plus 1 times 7, minus 10 times 0 9.