[Music]
In this video we will discuss an important class of stochastic processes in
continuous time ETA processes.
First, we will start with the definition,
then we will discuss, how to check,
whether the Ito process is a martingale
or not. And then we will provide two
forms, how we may write down the Ito
process.
First, the definition - the stochastic
process is called Ito process, if it can
be represented, as a sum of three terms a
constant Y0,
the second term is a Ito integral from 0
to T of AU times dWu plus the third
term: the ordinary integral from 0 to T
of BU times DU.
This wide class of continuous time
stochastic processes
has a a very simple intuitive property,
they behave locally like a Wiener
process with drift.
And we have an informal theorem for
Ito processes.
If the Riemann integral is absent in
their representation of an Ito process, so,
YT is just Y0, a constant plus an Ito
integral from 0 to T of AU times dWu, in
this case,  the
Ito process is a martingale. So, the best
guess of future value of an integral
plus constant is its current value. So,
expected value of YT given sigma algebra
information FS is just YS for S, less
or equal than T.
And we may also discuss the expected
value of an Ito process. For any
reasonable process BT we have an
informal theorem, that expected value of
ordinary Riemann integral from 0 to T of
BU times DU is just integral of the
expected value of BU times DU.
Basically, that is very intuitive, because
integral is just the sum expected value
of a sum, is a sum of expected
values. So, basically the the idea of the
proof of this theorem is to interchange
the order of summation and
expectation.
And, hence,
if we have the representation of an Ito
process like YT is Y0 plus stochastic
integral plus Riemann integral, then
expected value of YT is just Y0,
because it's a constant plus integral
from 0 to T of expected value of BU
times DU, because expected value of
stochastic integral is zero.
When we write the Ito process in the
full form, we need to write integrals, we
write YT equals to Y0 plus C integral
plus C integral, we need to write
this limits of integration
and to save space.
We will use this short form instead of
YT is the sum of Y0 plus
Ito integral plus three in an integral,
we will just use the compact short form
notation dYt equals to 80 times DWT
plus BT times DT. So, this is just a
shorthand notation, there are no special
meaning in dYt. That's not a random
variable, that's not a constant dYt
does not exist.
DWT does not exist.
dYt equals to AT times DWT plus BT
times DT, is only a compact counterpart
of the full form, when we write a short
form we really mean the full form.
Once again, DWT and dYt have no meaning.
Short form is  very useful probably in
simulations, because if we'd like to
simulate a stochastic time pass
of YT equals to Y0 plus
Ito integral plus Riemann integral. And
when we write the corresponding short
form dYt equals to 80 times DWT plus
BT times DT. Then we just think of a
small change  in time.  Let's imagine,
that the time changes by delta.
And, hence, the delta of our process Y
tYt plus delta minus Yt is
approximately equal to 80 times the
change of Wiener process WT plus delta
minus WT plus BT times the change of
times so times delta. And to simulate, to
run a simulation, we just create
randomly WT plus delta minus WT, using
normal distribution whith means 0 and
variance delta. So, this short form is
very useful in computer simulations.
Let's
look at one example. If I write DWT
equals to YT power 4 times DWT,
that basically means,
that YT is equal to Y0 plus integral
from 0 to TW power 4 times dWu.
If I write dYt equals to cosine of WT
times DT, I really mean, that YT equals
to Y0 plus integral from 0 to T cosine
of W Times DU.
And, hence,  using short form notation,
we may restate our informal theorem.
Ito process YT is a martingale, if and
only if, in the short form it is
written like dYt equals to 80 times dWt.
So, let's check a summary.
Ito  process is a sum of three terms a
constant and Ito integral, and all our old
friend Riemann integral.
Ito process will be a martingale
without Riemann integral in this sum.
And we often use short form with DT and
DWT. And, once again, DWT has no meaning,
it's just a short form to write less, and
we really mean a full form, when we write
a short form.
[Music]