[Music]
Let's calculate the price of an asset in
the framework of Black and Scholes model in this video.
We will use our previous results.
And then let's describe a contractor of a European type.
So, the contract pays you St. So, basically,
you receive one share, if as the price of
a share Su was never before 120
before time moment big T. And the
initial values are the following: as zero
the initial price of a share is 100, are
the risk-free interest rate is 0 0 5
sigma, the volatility is equal to 01
And the T, the final moment of time is
three. So, basically here is the problem.
We have an asset, that pays you St,
basically, gives you a share under some
conditions, not always you may receive
zero, you may receive one share, you may
receive Sd or you may receive zero. Okay,
and let's do experiments to solve this pricing problem.
Okay, let's subdivide the time interval
from 0 to T into 1000 smaller time
intervals. We will consider a discrete
version of our continuous time process.
Then we will specify the number of simulations.
Let us have ten thousands of simulations.
And let's calculate the final price of
our asset in every simulation. So, we will
keep track of final price of our asset.
So, we will reserve memory, so, we will
say numpty zeros, and we will reserve
space for N number of simulation values.
Okay, now the cycle.
For I in range and sim, so, that means I
will repeat this and same times.
First, I will calculate the trajectory of
Wiener process, I will calculate the
trajectory of share price, I will
calculate the final price of my asset,
and I just keep track of the final price.
Okay, so, let's create that trajectory of
our Wiener process get, Wiener trajectory.
We say T equal to T here and equal to N.
Okay, then we get that trajectory of timestamps.
And get time T equal to T and equal to N.
Then we create the trajectory of share
price. S will be equal to S0 times exponent of
here we have R minus sigma square root over two
times Te plus sigma times W. So, that's the
trajectory of share price in the Black and Scholes model.
Then we just calculate final price.
Now final price number I
is equal to S. The last value will have number n.
And the final price is equal to this
N only under the condition, that
maximal value of S is below 120.
Okay, basically, that's all we launch our
cycle, we wait a little bit.
And we need to calculate the discounted
expected value. So, we just calculate the discounted average.
In our terms, that would be exponent
of minus R times t, times mean value of our final prices.
And here we are. We have calculated the
fair price, the non-arbitrage price in
the framework of Black and Scholes model.
We should also check, whether our
experiments are stable or not. Let's just
relaunch this once again and see, if the price will fluctuate a lot.
Okay, we repeat our experiment, we check,
that, yeah, that's roughly the same value.
If we'd like to increase precision, we
should consider bigger value of N and
bigger value of number of simulations,
but, basically, our conclusion, that the
fair price of this asset is 38. Let's
analyze a little bit. How the
volatility of the share price will
influence the price of our asset? So,
let's, for example, increase the volatility of a share price.
So, let's edit to here, what will happen
with the price of our asset? Will it go
down, will it go up?
Okay, we just redo our experiments.
The previous value was roughly 38.
And now we got 23. So, when we increase at
least, that for these values, we have
considered. When we increase the
volatility of a share price, we see, that
the price of our asset goes down.
[Music]