[Music]
In this video we will introduce
Ito integral or stochastic integral. Our
introduction will be informal and
intuitive, because rigorous introduction
requires the concept of limits.
And we will not discuss it in our
introductory course, but our informal
definition will be enough to calculate
some simple examples and to work with
stochastic integral.
Let's define the Ito integral from 0 to
T of some stochastic process Au times
dWu, as a total net cash flow of a
strategy. If we treat Wu, as a price of
an asset at time moment U, and the Au, as
a quantity of the asset we have at time
moment U.
We agree, that WT is a bad model for the
price process, because for example WT may
be negative, and in most cases the price
cannot be negative, but the intuition is
perfectly fine.
We once again define their net cash
flow of a trading strategy, as an
integral from 0 to T quantity at time
moment U times G price at time moment U.
So, after the left G we have price before
letter D, we have quantity.
Using this simple intuition, we can
calculate all the deterministic
integrals too.
For example, let's consider integral from
2 up to 8 of 7 times Du. So, where is the
price, where is the quantity? 7 is the
quantity, and U is a price at time U. Okay,
so, we have two transactions to deal
with. The first transaction at time U
equal to 2, we buy 7 units of acid.
And the price at time moment U is just
U. Because U is a letter after D and,
hence, the price is equal to two. Okay, our
cash flow is minus seven times two,
transaction 2. At final moment of time, at
time moment U equal to 8, we sell our
seven shares, our seven units of asset.
But the price now is eight, because U is
equal to 8. And, hence, our cash flow is
plus seven times eight. And, so, the total
net cash flow the value of an integral
is minus 14 plus 56, or it's equal to 42.
If you check this integral, using all the
rules, you will get exactly the same
answer, but this interpretation is very
powerful. We can calculate net cash flow
of a trading strategy, using integrals.
That's very powerful idea, but obviously
this integral is very simple.
Okay, the next one. What is the integral
from 2 up to 8 of 5 times dWu? Now the
quantity is 5, and the price is given by
the stochastic process W.
Okay, we have two transactions once again.
The first transaction at time moment U
equal to 2, we buy five units. So, the
price of each unit is W2. And, hence, our
net cash flow for the first transaction
is -5 times W2. Yes, once again we
remember, that W2 may be negative, but
that's okay.
And transaction number two at time
moment U equal to 8, we sell our five
units of the asset, but the price now is
W8. Hence, the cash flow of the second
transaction is five times W8.
And the value of the stochastic integral,
.
we have calculated our first stochastic
integral! Bingo! Is -5 times W2 plus 5
times W8.
And we will use the adjustments
agreement. We will denote the upper limit
of integration by T. And
varying time will be denoted by the
letter U, and U will ordinary
range from 0 up to T.
The big problem with stochastic
integrals is, that all the integration
formals are wrong.
For example, let's try to calculate the
integral from 0 to TWU times dWu. It's
a very strange financial strategy,
because the quantity of an asset is
Wu, and the price of an asset is also Wu.
So, this strange strategy
prescribes us to
have two assets, two units of asset, if
the price is two. This strange strategy
prescribes us to have five units of
asset, if the price is five. Okay,
our all the intuition from Riemann
integral says, that should be one over
two WT squared minus one over two  W
0 squared, but it's wrong.
This guessed value is not negative,
because it's one over two times WT
squared, and it's zero or greater than
zero. But, obviously, when you are trying
to buy and sell Wiener process, if the
price changes randomly, then you can
obviously have negative net cash flow. So,
this all the answer is wrong.
So, we need new rules of integration.
In most cases the either integral cannot
be computed explicitly, it can be
simulated on computer. We can use its
properties, but
in very rare cases we can obtain
explicit expression.
For our purposes three cases will be
enough. The integral from 0 to T of 1
times dWu is just WT.
The integral from 0 to T of WU times
dWu will be equal to WT squared minus T
over 2. And the last one the integral
from 0 to T of exponent of  a WU
minus 1 over 2 a square root U times dWu,
we have a formula for this case, but in
general, there are no easy rules of
integration. But let's pay attention
for a small difference with ordinary
integral. The right hand side, the answer
sometimes can be positive, sometimes can
be negative. But if, for example you,
integrate a positive function from 0 to
T, you will receive a positive result,
when you are calculating ordinary
integral, and with stochastic integral it
can be negative with some probability.
Okay,
let's make a small summary, the
stochastic integral or Ito integral is a
total net cash flow of a strategy.
It can be rarely computed explicitly, but
it can be simulated.
And all rules of integration do not
apply, so, be careful, when you see a
stochastic integral with respect to Wu.