[Music]
This lecture is about option pricing.
In the first video we will discuss
discounted price process. We will start
by recalling, what discount it is in
continuous in discrete time. Then we will
state the theorem, that says, that every
european type asset can be replicated.
And then we will look at the pricing formula.
Okay, if XT is a price of a claim at time
moment T, we can re-express the same
future price and the current prices.
And in discrete time it's very easy. We
just divide Xt by 1 plus R power T or
just 1 plus R power minus T times Xt. In
continuous time it's little bit more
interesting. We divide Xt by exponent of
R power T or we divide Xt by exponent
of RT, or we multiply Xt by exponent of
minus RT. Then the discounting in
continuous time. What's the reason behind
this formula? The reason behind this
formula is the following exponent of R
for small R according to the to the
Taylor expansion is approximately equal
to 1 plus R.
And it's much easier to work with
exponent of R in continuous time,
because you can take derivative, you can
take logarithm and so on.
And just a small reminder:  if T is equal
to 0, then the discounted price and the
price are equal, because the multiplier
exponent minus RT or 1 plus R power
minus T are equal to 1.
Okay, let's ask the following question: is
a discounted share price a martingale?
It seems, that okay on average the share
price should grow, but, maybe, if we speak
about discounted share price, it will be
a martingale. Okay, let's use it, as lemma,
and let's calculate  the differential
of discounted share price.
First, we start with Ito's lemma. We have
minus R times exponent of minus Rt
times St Dt plus exponent of minus Rt
dSt. We may meet the second derivative,
because the second derivative with
respect to S2s is zero.
We simplify, where we rearrange the terms,
and we get exponent of minus Rt times St times.
In the brackets we have mu minus R times
Dt plus sigma times dWt.
So, the answer is no.
Under probability P short form has Dt inside it.
And when short form has Dt inside the
process is not a martingale.
So, S0 we cannot calculate, that 0 is the
expected value of discounted price.
But let's recall once again, that formula for differential, for
discounted share price it is exponent
minus rtSt times very familiar bracket.
Mu minus R times Dt plus sigma times dWt.
This familiar bracket is just sigma
times dWt star. Wow, that means, that
differential of discounted share price
is just exponent minus Rt times St
times sigma times dWt star. Wow, it has no
Dt term inside it. So, on the probability P star
short form has no Dt term inside.
Wt star is a Wiener process. And, hence,
the discounted share price is a
martingale under probability P star. So,
S0 is equal to expected value star of
future discounted price exponent minus
Rt times St, given current information,
that is described by sigma algebra F0.
Now let's move on to the next topic the replicating strategy.
And in the Black and Scholes model, every
european type asset can be replicated by
a self-financing strategy, that trades
shares and risk-free bonds.
At time T the portfolio contains Yt
shares and Zt bonds. So, the price of
portfolio Xt is equal to Yt times St, the
total price of all shares in the
portfolio plus Zt times Bt, the total
price of all risk-free bonds in the
portfolio.
But a strategy is self-financing the dXt
is equal to Yt times dSt plus Zt times
dBt, because we recall, that the meaning
of a stochastic integral is just the net
cash flow, when you have Yt shares, and
the share price is after the letter D.
Just a small remark european type asset
gives you a specified payoff at a fixed time moment big T.
And, once again, self financing strategy means that there are no exogenous capital inflow or outflow.
And, finally, let's test, let's State the
pricing formula.
As every asset can be replicated, using bonds and using share price.
And they discounted or price of a bond
is just a constant, the discount share
price is a martingale.
And every portfolio is a combination of
these two. So, we get the following informal theorem
in the Black and Scholes model the discounted price of every of any
European type asset is a martingale
under probability P star. Hence, the price
of any European type claim X0 is just
exponent minus Rt times expected value
star of future value
Xt given current information current
sigma algebra F0.
Once again Wt star is a Wiener process,
but on the probability P star not on the
probability P.
The link between Wt, and Wt star is Mu
minus rDt plus sigma times dWt equals to
sigma times dWt star.
And just a small reminder, what is the idea of the proof
of this theorem. Because every European
type asset can be replicated using
trading shares and bonds, discounted bond
price is constant, discounted share price
is a martingale, and the probability
measure P star. So, basically, the theorem
follows from this idea.
Let's proceed to the summary. European
claim gives payoff at a fixed specified
in the contract moment of time T.
The discounted price of any European
type claim is a martingale on the P star.
So, to calculate the price, we need to
calculate one expected value.
And the other main idea, that every
European type claim may be replicated.
And the pricing formula here it is X0 is
equal to exponent of minus Rt times
expected value star of Xt given current
information described by sigma algebra F0.
[Music]