[Music]
Welcome to our course on stochastic
calculus.
This lecture we will discuss Wiener
process and Martin Gales. And we start
with a short description of our course.
Our main goal is to price European type
options in the framework of Black
and Scholes model.
The main problem is a contradiction. Our
course is very short only four weeks. And
the mathematics behind the course is
very hard.
Soб we will provide sometimes informal
definitions and theorems. And we will
focus on problem solving and computer
simulations in Python.
Okay, Wiener process here it is.
And what is the formal definition behind.
First, we start with stochastic or random
process is basically a collection of
random variable indexed by a time
variable T. Mainly, we will work in
continuous time, so, XT the index T will
belong to any to the set of any positive
real numbers or zero.
And sometimes we will work in discrete
time. So, T maybe, 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 and so on.
And just a small notation remark:  when we
write brackets XT, and T greater or
equal to zero or just bracket 6T, we mean
a collection of random variables. And
when we write just XT without brackets,
we mean one a particular random variable.
Okay, now the Wiener process. The Wiener
process is defined by four  defining
properties. The first one is very easy. W0
is zero. So Brownian motion or Wiener
process starts at zero. The next property
is more interesting. The increments so WT
minus WS, the change of Wiener process, is
a normally distributed random variable
with mean zero and variance T minus S.
The third property that increment WT
minus WS is independent of the past
values of Wiener process.
And the last property. The trajectory of
Wiener process is continuous with
probability one.
So you may see a duck here. This is a
formal duck with a tie and a hat. So this
definition is perfectly rigorous. And
sometimes we will use less formal
definitions and you will see the less
formal duck.
Sometimes, later.
Okay. And here we will use our first
tradition. When we speak about two
arbitrary moments of time SNT, we usually
will suppose that S is before T. As in
the alphabet S is before T. So time
moment S is Before Time moment T.
Our main trick to study properties of
many stochastic processes will be divide
and concur.
That means future value of some process
will be known current Value Plus
unpredictable future change.
for the Brownian motion it seems trivial.
WT is past value WS plus the Change Plus
WT minus WS.
Okay. Our first exercise with exercise we
need to struggle. So we need a good
helmet and a sword.
Okay. Let's calculate the probability.
That W at time moment 10 is greater than
2 given. That you know some information
that W6 is 3.
Okay. the probability that W10 is greater
than 2 given our information is the
probability. We use our main trick. We
decompose future value into past value
and change. So that will be W6 plus
change W10 minus W6.
Okay. We may use the fact that W6 is 3
and we plug in it instead of W6.
Then we use the fact that W6 now gives
no information about the future change.
And we are done. W10 minus W6. According
to the defining properties of Brownian
motion is normally distributed with mean
0 and variance 4. Hence we standardize
it. We subtract 0 we divide by square
root of variance, we obtain standard
normal, random, variable.
And we use standard normal distribution
function f of U that is just the
probability that a standard normal
random variable Z is less or equal to U.
And hence our answer is just the
probability.
That is less than zero five. So it's
a probability distribution function at
0.05. And approximately using tables or
using computer, we can see that it's 0.69.
We will have a lot of gentlemen's
agreement to shorten the X position on
slides. So sS and T are arbitrary two Time
moments with S before T.
Wt will always denote a Wiener process
that will always denote a standard
normal random variable.
And F of U will denote the standard
normal distribution function.
Okay. Let's focus a little bit on the
property of independent increments.
Increment WT minus WS is independent of
the past values.
So W6 minus W4 is independent of W4
w3w1 and so on.
Or W6 minus W4 is independent of these
two increments.
And by the same argument we see that all
increments W6 minus W 4, W 4 minus W 3
and W 2.5 minus W1 are independent.
Or in more abstract notation if we have
many time intervals that are
non-overlapping.
Then the increments WT1 minus WS1 and so
on are independent.
Just a small remark. The right border of
an interval may touch the left border of
the next one, but it may not exceed it. In
this case of non-overlapping time
intervals the increments of Wiener
process are independent.
Let's calculate expected value and the
variance of a Wiener process.
Expected value of WT is expected value
of WT minus W0 is zero. The variance of
WT is variance of WT minus w0 is T by
the assumptions.
And for T greater than S covariance of
WS WT we use the same trick we decompose
the future value into
past value and future change, and hence
we see that the covariance is just the
the value of s that is before t.
For example covariance of W7 and W3 is
3.
Okay. We have two close friends of Wiener
process.
Brownian motion or winner process
with drift and scaling. When we multiply
winner process WT by some constant a and
when we add a trend B times T. We have a
stochastic process that is called
Brownian motion with drift and scaling.
And one more friend. If we take the
exponent of Brownian motion with drift,
we obtain a very usable stochastic
process that is called geometric bronial
motion.
In the framework of black and souls
model the share price is assumed to
follow geometric Brownian motion, so this
is a model of a price of a share.
Okay, here we see on the plots of these
two friends of Wiener process.
Okay, just more exercising, let's
calculate expected value of Brownian
motion with drift and scaling. Expected
value of 5 WT plus 60 and the variance
of the same process.
Okay, that's very easy expected value of
5wg plus 60 is 0 Plus 60. And the
variance of 5wt plus 60 is just 25 T,
because 60 does not influence the
variance.
Okay, sometimes to calculate harder
properties of Wiener processes and
the friends of Wiener processes, we will
need expected values of exponents. We
will just postulate them, that the
expected value of exponent of a z is
exponent of a square root of 2. And the
same property holds not only for
standardized
random variables Z, that  is normal 0 1
but for arbitrary WT.
these properties are obtained using
integration but we will not go into
details, but basically one needs to
calculate the integral of the function
times the probability density function
of the corresponding random variable.
and the expected value of exponent of ax
is so useful, that it has its own name
moment generating function.
for example, moment generating function
for a standard normal random variable is
exponent of a squared over 2.
why may we need a moment generating
function?
if you can take the derivative of a
moment generating function  with
respect to the variable
u. you will have expected value of x
times exponent of u x and if you plug in
the value 0 instead of U you will obtain
just expected value of x. if you repeat
this trick many times you see that
moment generating function is a funny
way to calculate a lot of expected
values. for example you take the
derivative twice and you get expected
value of x squared you calculate the
derivative three times and you plug in 0
instead of U and you get expected value
of x cubed and it's very useful to
calculate many expected value and to
study properties of stochastic processes.
so, a short summary: what is a
Wiener process? Wiener process is a
stochastic process with normal and
independent increments.
Wiener process with drift and geometric
Wiener processes are two friends of a
Wiener process. and the share price in
the black controls model is modeled by
the geometric Wiener process by
geometric Brownian motion.
and we have introduced moment generating
function that is used to calculate
expected values.
foreign
[Music]