[Music]
Let's get used to the Ito's lemma by considering  two examples.
We have two stochastic processes: we have
XD, that is T cube times WT squared and YT,
as ST squared, where ST has the same
dynamics, as the share price in a Black and
Scholes model. And we need to find DX DY,
and to recover the full form
corresponding to the short form with DX
and DY.
Let's do it.
Let's start with DX.
So, Ito's lemma says, that we should take the
derivative with respect to time. So, what
is the derivative with respect to time?
It's 3T squared times WT
squared times DT.
Plus.
We should add the first derivative with
respect to our stochastic process WT. So,
it will be T Cube times 2 WT
times GWT plus. And Ito's lemma says, that
contrary to the ordinary usual
calculus, in stochastic calculus we
should add one more correction term. So,
we should add 1 over 2.
The second derivative with respect to
WT. So, it will be T Cube times two times
DWT squared.
And we need to simplify dWt squared.
And we have
two simplifications rule.
Okay, our rules to simplify are: DWT times,
DWT is always equal to DT,
and DT times the anything is zero. So, I
will write separately DT times DT is 0.
And DT times dWt is also zero. So, we
have basically this simplification rules.
So, our DWT will be equal to DT.
And, hence, we may write:
three T squared
WT squared times DT
plus
2T cubed
WT times DWT
plus T cubed times, and we simplify the
WT times, DWT will be equal to DT.
Hence, we get a standard form for an
Ito process. We get 3T squared WT
squared plus T cube times DT
Plus
2T Cube WT times dWt. And this is the
expression for dXt. Okay, that is DxD.
And we can recover the full form.
So, if we have this expression for dXt.
Hence, XT itself is equal to sum X0
plus two integrals. The first integral is
Ito integral, and the second one is
the standard Riemann integral. Okay, so, we
have integral from 0 to T. I will write
the first one.
Or, maybe, that one, that is more
important for us.
I will change the variable to a
new name, so, instead of T, I will use A, U,
any other letter is okay.
Your cube WUDWU plus ordinary
Riemann integral, integral from 0 to T
3 U squared W
squared plus U cube
DU.
And this expression has some useful
properties. For example, I can immediately
say, whether XD is a Martingale, because I
have
this term
and the second term. The first term
is a martingale, X0 is a constant, but I
have one more term. So, I may immediately
conclude, that my XT is not a martingale.
Okay, let's move on to DSD.
All right,
we use the same Ito's lemma, and we have
dYt.
There are no T inside ST squared, so, we
just will take the second term of Ito's lemma
and the third one. Okay, so, the
first derivative with respect to ST is
2 ST times DST. Okay, I take the second
derivative plus one over two times
2 times DST
squared.
Okay, I plug in the value for DST, I know,
that DST is equal to M ST DT
plus sigma STDWT. That's the
expression for DST in the Black and Scholes
model.
And here I have a MSTDT plus sigma S
TDWT squared.
Inside these brackets I see, that
DT squared will be equal to zero DWT
times DWT will be DT, and DWT times DT
will be zero. Okay, so,
I have 2 MST squared DT plus 2 sigma ST
squared times DWT plus. Everything will
disappear, except one term. One term will
remain. It will be sigma squared
times ST squared times DT.
This is just
DWT squared.
Okay, and I have the short expression for
dYt.
And I might write the full form for dYt.
That means YT equals to Y0 Plus
stick a stochastic integral
from zero to D. Where is the stochastic
part? Stochastic part is here.
It is two sigma SU squared times dWu
Plus,
and I have ordinary integral from 0 to T.
Everything else is ordinary Riemann
integral. So, I will have a 2 MSU
squared plus sigma squared SU
squared times
DDU.
And this full form gives me some
properties of YT. Once again, I can
immediately check whether my YT is a
martingale. I have a constant, I have
stochastic integral, which is a
martingale, and I have some
other terms. And, hence, I conclude once
again, that my process YT is not a
martingale.
Hence, just have applied Ito's lemma twice, and we see, that basically it's
easy. It's a little bit more complex, than
the usual derivative. We need to take
the derivative twice, but, except this
small correction term, everything is easy,
and is as usual in ordinary calculus.
[Music]