[Music]
Now let's solve some real models.
Let's consider Vasicek interest rate
model. DRT is equal to 005
minus RT times DT plus 2 times WT. That's
a very simple model for interest rate,
that it's non-constant interest rate,
even stochastic interest rate, it changes
randomly over time. And let's solve for
it's expected value. Basically, what does
this model mean? This model means, that, if
RT is too big, is bigger, than 0 0 5, then
this term will be negative. So, there will
be a tendency to go down for RT, and
these terms to DWT, basically, intuitively
means, that is the source of randomness.
Okay, let's calculate expected value of
RT.
First step, we will recover full form
corresponding to this short form
notation. So, let's write full form first.
RTE is basically R0 plus, we transform
this expression into full form. Basically,
we replace T by some, as a letter by U,
and we write integrals. So, we write
integral from 0 to T
0 0 5 minus RU
DU plus
integral from 0 to T2 times dWu.
Okay, let's simplify, and let's take
expected value.
So, R0 is given,  this integral we
already know, that there are no, so, there
are, basically, two trading points we
should buy at time moment zero and sell
it time moment two, two shares with price
governed by WU.
And, hence,
this term equals 2 times 2
WT, that's our final value of the
portfolio minus 2 times W0.
And, hence, our
RT equals to 0 0 7 plus integral from 0
to t 0 0 5 minus RUDU plus 2 times WT.
And, so, RT is stochastic. And let's take
expected value.
So, I take expected value of RT, I get 0 0
7 plus.
When I have an ordinary Riemann integral,
expected value just goes inside ordinary
integral. So, it will be  integral from
0 to T expected value of 0 0 5 minus RUDU
plus expected value of Wiener
process is zero.
So, I get an interesting equation.
Expected value of RT is 0 0 7 plus
integral from 0 to t 0 0 5 minus
expected value of RUDU.
And for simplicity, let's denote this
function by some H by some
M of t.
Okay, we have M of T, that's a
deterministic function, because it's an
expected value. It is 0 0 7 plus
integral from 0 to T 0 0 5 minus M of
UDU.
Let's take the derivative.
M prime
is, we take the derivative with respect
to T. So, 0 0 7 will be transformed into
zero.
And, hence, I have a very interesting case.
I integrate from 0 to T, and I take the
derivative. If I take integral, then
derivative basically nothing happens, and
I just write the expression inside. I
have
the following fact, that if you
integrate from 0 to T, any deterministic
function H of UDU, and you take the
derivative after it. So, you have nothing
to do. You can just be lazy, and you will
not take integral, will not take the
derivative, and it will be just H of T.
Okay, in our case, that will be 0 or
0 5 minus
M of T.
Now we will solve our ordinary
differential equation. Let's move on.
We get the equation M or prime
equals to 0 0 5 minus M, where MT
is a non-random function. Okay, let's
write, DUTDT equals to 0 0 5 minus MTI
separate variables. So, I will move
the function M to the left hand side, T
to the right hand side. I will get D MT
divided by 0 0 5 times MT equals to DT.
I add the magic sign -
the integral.
And I just calculate this integral. I get
a logarithm of absolute value of 0 0 5
minus M t with minus, because I have
minus MT equals to T plus some
constant C0.
Now I multiply by -1. I get,
and I will take exponents, so, I will got
absolute value of 0 0 5 minus M T is
equal to
exponent of minus T times exponent of
minus C0.
This will be just another constant C1.
The absolute value of MT minus 0 0 5
is the same thing, as absolute value of
0 0 5 minus MT. So, basically, I can open
the absolute value. And I will get MT
minus 0 0 5
equals to
exponent of minus T times plus or minus
C1, depending, whether, we open the
absolute value is minus, so, plus. Okay,
this is just another constant C2. It is
not evolving in time.
And I have initial condition: my
initial condition is R0 is equal to 0 0
7. Okay, if initial condition is 0 0 7,
then I can calculate this C2. 0 0 7 minus
0 0 5 equals to exponent of
minus 0 times C2.
Hence, C2 is just 0 0 2.
And I got my final
answer. I just plug in C2 in my previous
answer, and I got the final expression. mu
T the expected value of RT equals to
0 0 5 plus
0 0 2 times exponent of minus T.
And let's draw this function, let's draw
this expected value to fill it better.
This is T. This is MT. And the starting
value R0
is 0 0 7.
And, then, when T goes up, this term goes
to zero.
So, eventually,
my function will tend to 0 0 5.
And do not forget, that, that's only
expected value of R0, and R0 fluctuates
around this expected value. So,
basically,
the actual random process  will
look like,
it will fluctuate around this
expected value.
That's all we have solved YC check model
at least for expected value of interest
rate.
[Music]