[Music]
We continue with Vasicek rate model. And now we will
find the solution of this stochastic
differential equation.
We will use a very powerful strategy.
Let's face simplify.
You can find the solution of a simple
equation and then modify your solution
to match the original equation. That's
very powerful and simple strategy -
simplify and modify.
Okay, let's do it. I will be very lazy, I
don't like this hard problem. I like
easy problems, so, I will replace the 0 0 5
by 0. I will replace this
two by zero. Let's get a very simple
equation. So, I will get an equation like
D and, obviously, this equation will not
be for interest rate R, but for some
other At. So, dAt has a much simpler
equation, so, it will be just minus At
times dt. So, it's a very simple
differential equations. There are
non-randomness inside, there are no dWt
terms. So, I can easily solve it using
ordinary methods. So, okay, I will have
dAt over At is just minus dt.
I will add integrals
and logarithm of absolute value. At
is minus t plus some constant. And I will
choose one simple solution
of this equation. So, I will consider C
equal to zero. So, I will simplify the
problem, as much as possible, and then I
will modify my simple solution. So, I will
consider C equal to zero, so, I will
simplify, as much as possible. I will
choose At greater than 0. And, so, finally,
my At is just exponent of minus t.
Okay,
the first step is done.
I have a solution of a much simpler
equation. And now I will modify this
solution to match the Rt from original
equation. Let's do this.
Okay, I will consider Rt, as my simple
solution At, that is just exponent of
minus t times some modification
correction term Bt.
So, this is a simple solution
of wrong differential equation. This is
simple solution of another differential
equation. And this is a correction factor,
because my equation for R is not an
equation for A, they are different.
And I will plug in this Rt in my
original equation. So, I will need to use
the Ito's formula for Rt. So, the Ito's
formula for Rt says, that
I should take first derivatives, I should
take second derivatives. Okay, let's do it.
First, derivative with respect to A is
just Bt. So, I will have Bt times dAt
plus. I apply Ito's lemma mod for
At times Bt. So, I will get At times dBt
plus.
Here I have
one over two times the second
derivative with respect to A is
zero, so, it is zero times Da squared plus.
What is a mixed partial derivative with
respect to A to B is just one. So, I will
have 2 times 1 times dAt times dBt
plus, what is the second derivative with
respect to BT, is 0 times DBT squared.
Okay, let's simplify everything I know.
Okay At is known, dAt is known, this is 0,
this is 0. Okay, let's look at this
term dAta times DBT.
Bt is a correction term, I don't know or
it's a little process, I don't know, it's
structure, but it's something like Dt
plus something like dWt.
And what is about dAt?
It is minus exponent of minus T
times Dt. So, this is just minus A of T
times Dt.
And I need to multiply
these two expressions,
using Ito's rule. but Dt times Dt is 0, Dt
times dWt is zero. Okay, that's very
simple.
So, now I have an expression for dRt. dRt
is Bt. Bt, I don't know, it will be pity.
What is dAt?
It is minus exponent of minus t times t
Plus
What is At. At is exponent of minus
t times dBt.
But from the other hand, finally, I can
use original
expression. dRt should be this
expression.
And I just use this original
expression, so, I will copy it. It is 0 0 5
minus, what is Rt. It's At exponent of
minus t
times correction Bt
times Dt plus 2d
Wt. Okay, let's look at this expression.
I have Bt times minus exponent
times Dt. The same term Bt exponent
and Dt. Okay, it will disappear.
What will I get? I will get here.
Let's move on.
So, I will have
exponent of minus t times dBt.
What are the remaining terms?
In the right hand side,
I have 0 0 5 times Dt plus 2 times
dWt. Whoa! That means, that dBt
is just equal to
0 0 5 times exponent of T times
Dt
plus 2
times exponent of t dWt.
Yoo-hoo! I'm happier! Why I'm happy?
I'm happy, because this expression for
dBt has no unknown  stochastic
processes, in the right hand side. This is
something deterministic. This is just
expression with exponent t dWt, it's
easy to simulate it. I'm happy.
And, finally, Bt.
Bt is some B0
plus integral from 0 to t 0 0 5 exponent
of t
exponent of U. I need a new name for a
variable Du plus integral from 0 to
T to exponent of U dWu
and
my RT is just a product of At
times Bt.
At is exponent of minus t. Bt is
completely known. The only mystery is
just this B0. Everything else
we can either explicitly calculate
this integral and for this integral, it
cannot be expressed in terms of
elementary functions, but it's easy to
simulate it. So, okay, this we made
calculate this integral. Or the
second one, it's easy to simulate it. What
is B0?
But how to calculate B0? I know that R0
is 0 0 7. R0 is 0 0 7.
0 is just one I plug in.
So, I may conclude, that B0
should be 0 0 7, because
R0 is a product of  0 times B0. And,
hence, our  equation is completely
solved. I may write a very long
expression, but that's the answer, it's
hard.
Let me write it. So, I need to write At
exponent of minus t times a big, big, big,
big, big, big expression. So, I will get 0 0 7.
plus
integral from 0 to t 0 0 5
exponent of U
Du plus stochastic integral
from 0 to T to
exponent of U times dWu. And we need to
close bracket. So, that's the expression
for Rt in the  Yc check interest rate
model. This integral we may calculate it.
It's not hard to do. So, it will be 0 0 5.
exponent of Uu
changes from 0 up to T. And it will be
0 0 5 exponent of T minus one
and the second integral,
we cannot simplify it, but it's easy to
simulate it
with computer simulated.
So, using  Ito's lemma, we  may have found the
solution of velocity interest rate model.
we have explicit formula for the
interest rate, we can simulate it, we can
study its properties and so on.
[Music]