[Music]
Let's move on to conditional values now.
First, start with conditional expected
value of 7W6 squared given, that we know
W at time moment 4. Okay, we will use the
same trick on the future value W6. We
will represent it, as past value W for
known value, plus increment, that means W6
minus W4.
If we do this substitution, we will get
7 times expected value of
W4 plus brackets W6 minus W4 squared,
given that we know W4.
And now let's open the brackets inside
the square. Okay, we get 7 times
expectation of W4 squared plus W6
minus W4 squared plus
2 times W4 times increment W6 minus W4
given, that we know W4.
Now there are basically two cases, we
need to consider. W4 is completely
known to us. So, we work with W4, as with a
constant, so we will move it out of
conditional expectation.
And the increment
W6 minus W4 is independent of what we
know of W4.
Okay, we get 7 times
W4 squared is fixed, we know it.  Plus
W6 minus W4 squared is independent of
what we know, so, we replace conditional
expected value with unconditional one.
Plus
we take out 2 times W4, we take out what
is known out of the expected value. And
when we take
conditional expected value of the
increment, we can forget W for our
information.
Okay, what do we know about the
increments of Wiener process? The
increments of Wiener process are
normally distributed with means zero and
variance T minus S, when T is greater
then S. So,
we get 7 times brackets W 4 squared plus.
The expectation of W6 minus W4 squared
is basically the variance of W6 minus W4.
So, it will be 6 minus 4, this value we
may treat it, as expected value of W6
minus W4 squared going or we may say
that it's a variance of W6 minus W 4
that's 6 minus 4.
And we get plus 2 times W4 times
expected value of increment and expected
value of the increment is zero.
Hence, we get our final answer. 7 times W
4 squared plus 14.
Let's move on to the variance.
We calculate the variance of two W6
plus W5 given, that we know W4.
Once again. We will decompose future
values into increments plus plus past
values, but we have two random variables
here, so we will need two increments.
Let's do this.
Basically, we consider time moment
for time, moment 5, and time moment 6.
We will work with W4
the increment W5 minus W4 and the
increment W6 minus W5.
And using this idea of three
independent random variables, our
calculations will be much easier. Let's
do it.
Okay, we will have variance of two, I
will write W6 minus W5
to work with increment. Okay, but I have a
plus one W5,
so I will put everything back, so, I will
write three W5, so ,I have two w six and
one W5 as I wish. And now I will write
minus three W4,
and I will put them back plus three W4
four given W4.
Okay, this expression now I see, that I
have one increment, the second
independent increment and past value,
that I know. Okay,
my calculations are almost finished.
I have variance of 2 times W6 minus W5
plus 3 times W5 minus W4. I know W4, so, it
does not influence the variance and it's
independent of two other increments, so,
while I will simply emit my
last term. and I will emit my information,
because these two increments are
independent of what I know. So, I just
write
bracket here.
And I have
four times variance of W6 minus W5 plus
9 times variance of W5 minus W4.
Once again the variance of incremental
Wiener process is just difference of
time.
And I have 4 times 6 minus 5 plus
times 5 minus 4, and I get
13.
Let's move on to the last case to the
probability. We will estimate, sorry,
calculate probability, that 3 times W6 is
greater than 2 given, that we know W4.
Okay.
Let's subtract conditional expected
value, let's divide by conditional
variance and we will have a standard
normal distribution, and we can use CDF
cumulative distribution function to get
probability.
Okay, so, we just stop for the
moment,
and we calculate
conditional expected value of three w
6  given W4 it will be three.
Times  expected value of W6 given W4.
And, using our  famous trick of
decomposing future value into past value,
that is known plus independent increment,
we will get three times w 4.
If we do the same thing with
variance, variance of three w6 given
W4 will be 9 times variance of W6 given
W4.
I use my decomposition variance of W4
plus W6 minus W4, given W4.
This term
is fixed.
So, it is not influencing variance. And
the increment
is independent.
This one is fixed the other one is
independent.
So, I remove a fixed term that is known,
that does not influence variance.
And I get
9 times variance of W6 minus W4, given W4.
And here we have independence, and we can
just emit our information, it's useless.
And the variance of  increment of
Wiener process is just difference of
time moments. So, we get 9 times 6 minus 4
we get 18.
So,
to calculate this probability, we need to
standardize a random variable. So, we
subtract variance, we divide by square
root of variance, and we get the answer.
Okay, so, we will have here probability of
three W6 minus. We subtract
conditional expected value.
We subtract
3 W4,
we divide by square root of variance
conditional variance.
We do the same thing with 2 2 minus 3W
4 divided by square root of 18. Even W4.
Hence,
this left hand side has normal 0,1
distribution.
And that is known value,
so, we get
our last step.
We get 1 minus probability, that a
standard normal random variable will be
less
than
two minus 3 W4 divided over 18 given
that W4, we treat at as a constant.And
finally, we get 1 minus cumulative
distribution function at the point 2
minus 3 W4 divided by square root of
18.
Bingo! we have calculated all conditional
values, conditional expected value,
conditional variance and conditional
probability.
[Music]