[Music]
We will simulate trajectories of Wiener
process.
We use many libraries like pandas, numpy,
seaborn.
So, we start with our first function. Our
first function, we will call it get time.
This function will give us time moments:
first time moment, second time moment and
so on. Evenly spaced from 0 to big T. So,
this function will take big T, as an
argument. Let it be one by default and
the number of segments.
Let it be by default 1000 small
segments.
And, so, my function will just return
evenly space it. So, I use numpy space
function. The first argument is starting
moment of time. In our setting time
starts from zero. Final moment of time
will be just T, and the number of time
points should be N plus 1. Why? Because if
I subdivide a big
time interval into two smaller interval,
I will have three points one in the
beginning, one in the middle, one and in the
end. So, here I write the number of points:
it will be N plus one. So, basically,
that's our first function. Let's check,
whether it works, get time, Let T be equal
to 2, and  let's subdivide it
into 20 time intervals, so, we should get
21 time points. The first time point is
zero, the last time point is two and all
other points are evenly spaced between
them. Okay, our first function is ready.
Let's move on. Let's create the function,
that will give us the increments of
Wiener process for every
interval, for every small interval.
Okay, we will create this function. Get
Wiener
increments.
And this function
will take big T.
We'll take the number of small intervals,
and this new function will be stochastic
function, and, sometimes, we would like to
have
the exactly the same trajectory of
Wiener process, that is stochastic, but
sometimes, we would like to have, the
exactly, the same trajectory of
stochastic process twice. So, we need
sometimes to replicate exactly the same
trajectory, so, we will provide here, as a
seed. Seed is an initial condition to
make a generation of pseudo-random
numbers
replicable.
Okay, so, basically, what shall we
calculate here? First, we will create
random number generator. It will be
random
default
and random number generated
with a seed, as initial value. Then we
will say, that standard deviation for a
delta T. The standard deviation is the
square root of delta T. So, we will write
S square T of T over N. T Over N is a
length of small time interval. So, the
standard deviation of Wiener process
increment is square root of T over N. And
here we will create the deltas of Wiener
processes like RNG normal. And we will
say, that mean value is zero.
Standard deviation is SD, and the number
of
increments we need to generate, is
exactly N.
Okay, and we just return this delta W
vector.
Okay, let's check that our function works.
Get
Wiener
increments T is equal to 2. Let's
say 20 increments, and let's say, seed
will be equal to 777.
Okay, we have increments of Wiener
process. And this function, if I launch it
twice, I will get exactly the same result.
If I will emit the seed,
I will get new results, new random
results every time.
Okay, let's move on. How may we transform
increments into trajectory of Wiener
process? We just should calculate
cumulative sum.  Let's get, let's
create new function,
get Wiener trajectory.
And this function takes T, that is one by
default, and N that is 1000 by default seed,
that is none by default.
And the first step we get and
Brownian motion increments.
Delta V is
get Wiener increments.
Okay, I will just copy this code
seed, is seed tea is provided by the user,
and N is provided by the user.
And what about W's? So, we create the
vector of W's. Let it be numpy zeros,
we calculate, we just should have N plus 1
points for N increments. The first one
should be zero.
And VW from first to the last
should be just equal the accumulative
sum.
So we add them, and accumulate the sum
of
delta V, delta W, and we return this
generated vector of Wiener process
trajectory.
Okay, let's check, that our new function
works. Let's calculate,
get Wiener
trajectory. We may supply T, we
may supply N,
and we may emit seed to make
absolutely random trajectory.
Okay, now we may plot it already. We can
get our first plot SNS. Let's use a line
plot,
and let's use, as X we will get time.
And for Y we will get trajectory,
that should be our first plot.
Okay, that is the plot of a Wiener
process. And now, as we can freely
generate many trajectories,
we can study its properties. For example,
let's calculate the probability, that
this random trajectory will
hit the value of 2 before time moment
three.
Okay, let's
calculate the probability,
that WT
will hit 3 before T equal to 2.
Okay, let's move on.
We will simulate many trajectories, and
we will count trajectories for, which
the highest value of Wiener process
was higher than three.
Okay, let's introduce a new concept
number of simulations, that be the number
of simulations equal to ten thousands.
Okay, and
in the beginning, we have zero good
trajectories.
And we will count good trajectories, we
will add plus one for every trajectory,
that hits free before time moment T
equal to two.
Okay, so,
let's say I in range and scene. What
shall we do? We shall create a random
trajectory. W will be get Wiener
trajectory of TN.
Let it be T equal to 2, and will be
equal to one thousand. Okay, we get the
Wiener process trajectory.
Then we will
add plus one for every trajectory, that
has a maximum value higher than three.
Okay, if  maximal value of W is
higher than 3, we should add plus 1 to
the number of good trajectories. So, we
say good
trajectories.
Let's say this plus enter will increase
our variable  good trajectory. So, we
increase it by plus one.
And then, after this cycle, we should just
divide the number of good trajectories
by the number of  the total
number of all trajectories. And the total
number of volt reject resist number of
simulations
together,
and we wait a little bit.
And we see  the probability, that
Wiener process will hit this border, is
equal to zero zero three. We should
understand, that this is the empirical
value. And to obtain this value with
higher precision, we should make the
number of divisions,
and number of intervals, as high as
possible. The number of simulations, as
high as possible.
And, honestly speaking, only infinite
values will give us the true probability,
but, if we will put infinity in N or in
number of simulations, we will weight
infinite amount of time. So, we may just
experiment and check, whether
it is stable or not. So, let's launch the
second time. And we see, whether the
answer is  different, the answer is
more or less the same. We may check,
whether it will change with a high value
of N, because, honestly speaking, we have
replaced continuous time process with
discrete process with five or one
thousand observations.
Let's check.
And we see, basically, that the result is
stable, so, there is a good estimate of a
probability, that WT will hit 3 Before
time moment T equal to 2.
[Music]