[Music]
In this video we will discuss the concept of conditional expected value.
We will start with a sigma algebra,
or an object to model knowledge to model
information, then we will discuss a
conditional expected value and its
properties, and then we will move on to
the conditional variance.
Okay, let's start with modeling
information. Imagine the following
situation: John knows the value of a
random variable X. Maria knows the value
of a random variable X, and she knows
more, she knows also the value of random
variable Y.
So intuitively we understand that Maria
knows more. But how do describe this
difference from mathematical viewpoint?
How to describe this difference in
knowledge mathematically?
And, we introduce informally the
concept of sigma algebra.
Here we have an informal duck, so this
definition is a little bit informal, but
it conveys the intuition right. The sigma
algebra generated by random variables X.
And Y is a collection of all addends,
that can be stated in terms of these two
random variables.
We denote it by sigma of X and Y. And
let's discuss an example.  The sigma
algebra generated by random variables X
and Y contains all events, that can be
stated in terms of X and Y. For example, X
is less than five. This event in the
description uses only the variable X. So,
it's contained in the sigma algebra. The
avid X greater than 2Y is in this sigma
algebra. The event sine of Y is greater
than cosine of X, is contained in this
sigma algebra. So, Sigma algebra is a big,
big, big, big list of events. There are
really usually, there are infinitely many
events in a sigma algebra.
And now we can model information. So, John
knows the value of X. So, his sigma
algebra is generated by X. So, this list
of events contains all the events of the
type: X is greater than 1, X belongs to
the interval from 7 to 8. Everything that
can be stated in terms of X.
Mary knows more, so, her sigma algebra has
more evidence inside it.
And basically, in mathematical terms
the sigma algebra F
of John is a subset of sigma algebra F
of Maria.
Let's move on to the concept of
measurability. Sometimes, information
contained in a sigma algebra is enough
to calculate
the value of some random variable. For
example, if you have enough information
to calculate the value of R of a random
variable R, we say, that random variable R
is measurable with respect to sigma
algebra F. And here's definition is more
or less formal. So, sigma algebra
generated by R. So, knowledge
to find R, to find out R, is less than
your knowledge F. Knowledge is a list of
all events you know.
We say once again that sigma R is a
subset of sigma algebra F, that means in
plain wards that information in F, is
sufficient to calculate the value of R,
but maybe you know more random variables,
maybe you know some other random
variables as well.
And we have informal CRM. If a random
variable R is measurable with respect to
sigma algebra generated by X and Y,
then it can be represented as a
deterministic function of X and Y.
So, if a knowledge contained in X and Y
is enough to find out R, that means R can
be calculated as a function of X and Y.
And now let's move on to the main
concept of this block. The best
prediction of a random variable R given
Sigma algebra F
is called conditional expected value, and
it's denoted expected value of R given F.
First, I should point out that
F is a
sigma algebra. So, it's a list of events.
And then I should point out the
difference between conditional expected
value, expected value of R given F, and
ordinary expected value, expected value
of R.
If I know X and Y, my best prediction
of R may depend on X and Y. So, in general,
expected value of R given F is a sigma
algebra, while ordinary usual
unconditional expected value of R is a
constant.
Let's discuss the notation a little bit.
When the sigma algebra is some general
sigma algebra, we just use expected value
of R vertical bar given F.
And in a particular case of of a sigma
algebra generated by random variables X
and Y, we can write in full form expected
value of R given sigma algebra generated
by X and Y, or we simply write expected
value of R, given X and Y.
Sometimes we can simplify conditional
expected value, and sometimes we can emit
conditioning. The first case is when R is
independent of X and Y. So, knowledge of X
and Y is useless in predicting the value
of R. So, that means the best prediction
of R given, that you know
X and Y, is independent of X and Y,
because your knowledge is useless. And
it's equal to expected value of R. That
represents the situation, when you know
nothing useful about R.
And the second case, it's a little bit
strange, but if you think a little bit
it's natural. Expected value of
conditional expected value of R, given F,
is an ordinary expected value of R. What
does this mean?
The average of the best guess is the
average of the predicted variable. Yeah.
If it's your best guess, then you should
be right on average.
And the other extreme case is the case,
when the random variable R is completely
known. So, that means in formal terms
measurable with respect to sigma algebra
F. Then you may treat it like a known
constant.
That means expected value of R given F,
If your information in F is enough to
calculate the exact value of R, and the
conditional expected value is just R.
Or going back to our Wiener process,
expected value of 2 exponent of 5 WT,
given that you know WT is 2 times
exponent of 5 WT.
Or some more, more complicated
formulas. Expected value of 2 RS plus R
squared given sigma algebra F, and you
have enough information to calculate R.
So, you treat R like a constant. You move
it out of the expected value, that gives
you 2R times expected value of S given F.
Maybe you have enough information about
this, maybe not, plus R squared.
And now the last concept the concept of
conditional variance. The conditional
variance of R given sigma algebra F is
the conditional expected value of the
squared error of the best prediction.
Let's write in formulas. Variance of R
given F is equal to expected value of
delta square root given, that we know F.
Well, delta is a prediction error. So, that
means R the value of R minus best
prediction expected value of R given f.
And by analogy we can see the formula,
that conditional variance of R given
sigma algebra F is expected value of R
squared, given sigma algebra F minus the
squared value of conditional expected
value of R given F. This formula mimics
the formula for ordinary unconditional
expected value, maybe you recognize it.
Now let's move on to the properties of
conditional variance. Irrelevant
information may be emitted like in the
case of expected value. If R is
independent of your knowledge, your
knowledge is described by
sigma algebra F. Then expected value of R
given sigma algebra F is just expect
value of R. And the same is true for the
variance, conditional variance, so far
given, that you know F gives you
nothing useful about R, so it's just a
variance of R.
And E the other extreme case. If R is
completely known or in mathematical
terms is measurable with respect to
sigma algebra F, then we may treat R like
a constant.
So, for example, with  Brownian motion.
Variance of two exponent of 5Wt given,
that you know WT. So, for you WT is
completely predictable. It's like like a
non-constant. So, the variance is zero, the
conditional variance.
And more complicated example: variance of
2 RS plus R squared, given sigma algebra
F, has enough information to exactly
calculate R.
So, 2R is moved out of the variance with
square root, with square. You multiply it
by conditional variance of S, given
signals per F plus 0, because R squared
works like a constant.
And let's
provide a small summary.
Sigma algebra, sigma of X and Y is a
collection of all events that can be
stated using random variables X and Y.
For example, it contains the event X is
equal to Y, and many, many more other
events.
Conditional expected value, expected
value of R, given X and Y, is the best
prediction of R using the random
variables X and Y.
And finally, conditional variance of R,
given random variables X and Y is a
conditional expected value of the square
root error of the best prediction. And a
little bit later, we will see, that
basically, the price of an asset and a
black Insurance model is just a
conditional expected value.
[Music]