[Music]
In this video we will discuss the properties of
stochastic integral.
First, we will start with the common
properties of Ito integral with our old
friend Riemann integral. Then we
will discuss a very simple property, that
the expected value of
Ito integral is just 0. And then, we will
discuss Ito isometry, that can be used
to calculate the variance of a
stochastic integral.
Let's start with some basic properties,
that are common between Riemann integral
and stochastic integral with respect to
dWu.
If you have two non-overlapping time
intervals, the time interval from A to B
plus integral with the interval from B
to C, you can just use the common
interval from A to C of XudWu.
The second property: if you integrate
from A to A, then you have no time to
make money, and your net cash flow is
zero. And the last property, that you can
move out constant out of the integral,
that is a common property of Ito
integral and the agreement integral.
Now the property, that stochastic
integral has zero expected value. The
intuition here is very very simple: if
you buy and sell the Wiener process, so,
if the price is completely random, it may
go up and down with equal probability, so,
intuition says, that the expected net
cash flow should be zero. And, indeed, we
have informal theorem, that for any
reasonable process XT measurable with
respect to the natural filtration FT of
the Wiener process WT, expected value of
stochastic integral from 0 to T, of XU
times dWu, is zero.
And there is a property, that is called
Ito isometry, that describes how to
calculate the variance of stochastic
integral. So, the variance of integral
from 0 to T, of X U times dWu, is equal to
ordinary integral, old Riemann integral
from 0 to T, of expected value of XU
squared times DU.
Let's solve an exercise.
Let's find expected value of I of T and
variance of I of T, if I of T is an
integral from 0 to T of WU squared
times dWu.
Let's start with expected value OH, it's
simple, it's just zero.
Now, what about the variance?
We just square the stochastic process
inside the integral, so, it will be double
WU power 4. We calculate expected value
of it, and we integrate with respect
to W with respect to DU and not with
respect to dWu.
And, hence, we know, that expected value of
W power 4 is just 3U squared, and
the integral of this expression is just
T cube.
So, let's recap the properties of Ito
integral. It has zero expected value,
that's very simple.
Using the property, that is called Ito
isometry, one may calculate the variance
of a stochastic integral.
There are some common properties of
Ito integral and Riemann integral, but be
careful, in general, old integration rules
do not apply.
[Music]