[Music]
In this video we will simulate the trajectory of
stochastic differential equation. We will
use a code, we have created during two
previous weeks.
And we will simulate the trajectory of
risk of interest rate and the Vacicek
interest rate model. Initial value is 007,
and the stochastic differential equation,
that governs the dynamics of interest
rate: is DRT equals to
005 minus Rt times Dt plus 0 0 2 times
dWt.
Okay, let's create our function.
Def get as a solution.
We should specify the final moment of
time. We should specify the number of segments.
And we will specify initial value.
Okay, first, we will calculate them,
deltas of Wiener process.  Delta W will
be get winner increments of T.
And, so, we will need also seed here.
Seed will be none by default.
We will need T and and seed. Okay, we
got Brownian motion increments.
then we will calculate the trajectory of Wiener process.
We have already done this.
We can just copy these part of the code from the previous function.
Okay, we got the values of Wiener process,
the values of time stamps.
Then let's say Dt is T Over N to
simplify some calculations.
Okay, let's create that trajectory of our
solution R, that trajectory of R. First, we
will fill it with zeros.
We will get N plus one zeros.
Initial value is specified by our R0.
And then we will create a big cycle. We
will calculate the values of R one by one.
So, four I in range N.
What should we do? We should calculate
the delta R, and we should add it to the
previous value. So, basically, the logic is
very simple. First, we calculate delta R,
then we say, that our number I plus 1 is
equal to R number I plus delta R.
And, basically, we return that trajectory.
Okay, how delta R is calculated, and this
is exactly our stochastic differential
equation. So, basically we may copy it.
Okay, we will copy it here. And we replace
our Dt is Dt. So, we just add here
multiplied by Dt. What is RT? RT is a
previous value of our process R. So, it
will be Ri.
Okay, and here we got 0 0 2 times Dw. And
what is dWt? It is a delta W number I.
And we are done. So, let's check, whether
everything works.
We should provide some initial value for
R0. Let it be 0 0 5.
Okay, and now let's see the trajectory.
Okay, let's create, T will be
get time from T from T equal to 0 up to three.
Yeah, I don't know the initial value was 0 0 7.
Okay, we got the time, we go to 3 N
equal to one thousand.
Maybe, we should make them,
maybe, we should write them before
our function. Okay, T, and then we got T and N.
Then we will get the trajectory. R will
be get, as the solution.
Let me say T and R0 equal to 0 0 7.
And that's all.
Now we may plot our solution.
We use the C born line plot function.
The horizontal, on the horizontal axis we
will plot our time stamps. On the
vertical axis we will plot our
trajectory of our risk-free interest rate.
And we see, that this risk-free rate fluctuates around some
value. Let's check, how the plot will
change, if we will use different values.
So, let it be more sensible to the
deviations from the long run equilibrium.
So, let's multiply here by two. Yeah, let's
change a little bit the equation, let's
multiply here by 5. So, this will make
our trajectory very sensitive to the
deviations from these 0 0 5.
When RT will be much bigger than 0 0 5,
this term will be
negative and big by absolute value. So,
the interest rate should feel the
pressure to go down to value 0 0 5. So,
let's multiply by 5.
Well, multiply by 5 here.
Okay, and let's look what will change.
Okay, and we see that it goes from 0 0 7
to 0 0 5 or faster.
And we can experiment, then we can study
the properties of stochastic
differential equations solutions  in this manner.
[Music]