[Music]
We will know, how to price  different contracts in
the Black and Scholes model. We
need just to calculate expected value.
And we have already considered a
contract, that pays you at time moment t
equal to 2 S2 cube. And we have found,
that the no-arbitrage price of this
claim is just  0 Cube times exponent of
4R plus 6 sigma squared.
Okay, and it's also possible to replicate
this contract, this claim in the
framework of the Black and Scholes model. And
my question now is: how to start the
replicating portfolio? So, how many shares
I need to buy initially? How many units
of cash account I need to buy to
replicate these X0?
Okay, so, from one point of view
Xt can be completely replicated, using
shares and units of cash account. So, Xt
is just, if I buy Yt shares, so yt,
small y, is the number of shares. So, in
shares I have this sum of money. Yt is
the number of shares, St is a share
price. Plus I have Zt units of cash
account. So, I have Zt times Bt.
Bt is a cash account, what does it mean.
So, if in the beginning I have one dollar,
I invested in all. And
if B0 is one, then Bt is just exponent of
Rt. Okay, so, this is the price of my portfolio.
And by our interpretation of stochastic integral,
dXt is just Yt times dSt plus Zt
times dBt. Or we may write it like Yt
times, we just plug in the expression for
dSd. it will be mu St Dt plus sigma St dWt plus.
We also plug in the expression for dBt.
If Bt is just exponent of Rt, then we
have, dBt will be equal, we take the
derivative with respect to T. That's a
non-stochastic process. So, we have R
times exponent of Rt times Dt or just R times Bt Dt.
Okay, so, we have that times R times Bt Dt.
Okay, let's focus on their coefficient before dTe.
So, we have here
mu Yt St plus zTr Bt times Dt plus.
And we have the the other term, that is Yt sigma St dWt.
Okay, that will be the term of interest.
Or more specifically we will look at this term.
Now let's recall, that Xt may be expressed,
as a function of St and t. Okay, we also
have another approach Xt is a function of T and St.
We haven't recovered this function
for urbanity, but it's possible. But we
know, for example, that X0 is just S0
cube times exponent of 4R plus sigma squared.
Okay, so, we may also derive the general
formula for XT, using the eXp the expected value star of discounted X2.
But our goal is to find
only the starting values of replicating portfolio.
So, X0 will be sufficient. Okay, we will
apply it as Ito's lemma. Ito's lemma say, that
dXt should be equal to, what should be
equal to F of prime with respect to t times Dt
plus F prime with respect to S times dSt plus.
It is correction term 1 over 2 times F
prime prime with respect to S with
respect to S times dSt squared.
Okay, let's plug in the expression for dSt.
We will have F Prime with respect to t times Dt plus
F Prime with respect to S
times mu sTd d plus sigma St dWt.
Plus 1 over 2 F prime prime with respect
to S, what is DS squared?
If I will square this expression, I
will receive only sigma squared times
St squared times dWt squared, that is, that is equal to Dt.
And, basically, that's all. Okay,
let's look at our term with mu St. What is mu S?
Okay, in the first, so, I have two expressions.
For Xt, for dXt, I have two expressions for dXt.
And let us look at the coefficient before mu St.
So, I'm interested in a coefficient before mu St.
In the first expression, what is before muSt.
So, before mu St I have exactly
the number of shares, I need to hold in
my replication portfolio.
That is YT, the number of shares I need to have in
my replicating portfolio. What is the
expression before mu St
muStdt, yeah, muStdt in the second expression.
In the second expression, before muStdt
I have F prime with respect to S,
and to make my portfolio, replicating
portfolio, I need to have these values equal.
So, Yt should be F prime with respect to S.
And, hence, I almost have everything I need.
So, Y0. The numbers of shares to start the
replicating portfolio is just the
derivative of my initial formula for X0.
So, I will take my initial formula plus 6 sigma squared.
And I will take the derivative with
respect to S. So, it will be 3, as 0 squared times
exponent of 4R plus 6 sigma squared.
And this value is equal to 3 times 100
times exponent of 4R. R is 0 0 5, so, 4R is
0 2 6 sigma squared is 0 0 6.
So, I have 0 26 here.
And it will be 3 times, 100 times, approximately, 1.3.
And I will have here, this is
approximately. And I will have, and I will have roughly 390 shares.
So, to start the replicating portfolio I need roughly
390 shares, and which some should be invested in the cash account.
So what is the value of zero? What is
zero? But that 0 is just X0 minus Y0 times S0.
Because at the moment time t equal to 0, the price of
one dollar is one dollar. If the price of
my portfolio is X0 at start, and
I'm replicating it using  Y0
shares, each of them has a price, as 0.
So, this is the price, this is the number
of dollars, I need to have to start the
replicating portfolio. Okay, and we will
have 1297, approximately, minus 390 times, the price of one share is 10.
So, I will have 1297 minus 3090 nine hundreds. This value will be
negative. That's completely okay, because
in the replicating portfolio we may
borrow, that means. So what does it
mean negative or number of dollars? So,
that means, we need to borrow.
And, hence, the value is. So, we
obtain - 2603 dollars.
Okay, so, we not only know the initial
price X0. X0 is roughly 1297 dollars. So,
that's the initial price of our claim.
But we know, how to start the replicating
portfolio for this claim? To replicate we
need to borrow, so, we need to borrow
2603 dollars and to buy 390 shares.
This is the start value of replicating
portfolio, and then we will just continue
to use their identity, that dynamically,
we will use identity, that Yt should be
always equal to F prime with respect to
current share price. So, if we will
maintain this equality every time, then
we will obtain the replicating portfolio for our claim.
[Music]