[Music]
Okay, so, let's consider the process XT
equals to WG squared plus alpha T. And
let's
find out, when it's a martingale,
because martingales are useful in
pricing options.
Okay, what is a short form for dXt? We use Ito's lemma.
We say: wow! We need to take
the derivative with respect to T, that is
alpha times DT plus. We need to take
derivative with respect to WT, because
it's the unique stochastic process, we
have in the right hand side. So, it will
be 2 times WT times dWt plus. In Ito's lemma
we have additional correction
term.
And, hence, we will have 1 over 2 times
second derivative with respect to WT. It
will be 2
times. We will have, hence, here DWT
squared. Okay, let's simplify. DWT
according to our symbolic algebra is
just DT.
Hence, we get alpha DT plus 2 WTDWT
plus, and we have one times DT.
Okay, let's rewrite the short form.
We have dXt is just equal to alpha
plus one
DT
plus 2 WTDWT.
If we recover the full form
corresponding to this short form,
,
we will get XT equals to X0 plus
integral from 0 to T alpha plus 1 DU
plus integral from 0 to T
to WUDWU.
And we know, that this is a constant.
We may even found find out, that X0 is W0
squared plus alpha times zero. This is
honestly zero.
This is a martingale.
A constant plus a martingale is a
martingale, but this term
in general is not a martingale. But we
see, that when alpha is equal to
-1, this term will be killed. So, our
answer, that XT is a martingale,
if and only if
alpha is -1. Otherwise, these Riemann
ordinary integral will not be zero, and
the XT process will not be a martingale.
And now let's continue with the next
process, let's consider their Y process.
We also need to find out, when YT is a
martingale, and even more we need to find
some expected value. Okay, YT is an
exponent of alpha WT plus beta T, I
have two parameters here, I'm scared, but
let's do it.
Okay,
here our F of T and WT is exponent of
alpha WT plus beta T.
Okay, let's calculate F prime with
respect to T.
It will be beta times original
exponent alpha WT plus beta T or we may
just shortly write it like beta times
YT.
Okay, let's calculate F prime with
respect to WT. By the same logic, I will
obtain alpha
times exponent of alpha WT plus beta
T or just alpha times YT.
If I take the second derivative with
respect to my stochastic processes,
then I will have F prime prime WTWT
is alpha
times alpha times YT,
by the same logic. Now let's plug in
everything we have found into the Ito's lemma.
Okay, we have dYt equals 2
beta YT times DT Plus
alpha
YT times dWt plus correction term.
1 over 2
times
alpha squared times YT
times DWT squared.
We remember our symbolic simplification
rules, that DWT times DWT is just DT.
So, I get a very simple expression,
that dYt is just
beta YT
plus 1 over 2 alpha squared YT times DT
plus alpha YT DWT.
That's the expression for dYt.
Let's recover the full form.
Let's look at the full form, what is the
value of YT?
YT is just sum Y0 a constant plus a
martingale.
So, we will have integral from 0 to T
alpha YUDWU plus a term,
that is not a martingale in general. Plus
Riemann integral from 0 to T
beta y YU plus 1 over 2 alpha squared
YUDU.
That is a constant,
that is a martingale.
And this is probably
the thing, that will
make our YT non-martingale process.
So, how may I get rid of this
Riemann integral? Oh, I need to set up
beta equal to minus 1 over 2 alpha
squared. If I will do like this,
the value inside the integral will be
zero, the integral will be zero, and, hence,
my YT will be a martingale. Hence, this is
the necessary and sufficient condition
to make my process a martingale.
Okay, now let's see, how this
conclusion may help us to find expected
values.
So, let's find out expected value of
exponent of alpha times WT.
This process is not a martingale, we know it,
but I can make it a Martingale. So, I know
by definition
of a martingale and our calculations,
that the process YT, that is exponent of
alpha times WT minus alpha squared over
2 times T, this process is a martingale.
But what does it mean - the process is a
martingale? Martingales have many useful
properties, for example, expected value of YT,
given YS
or, whatever,
Y where S,
where YT and YS are two values, and S is
a time moment before T. So, in this case,
expected value of YT given YS is just YS.
In particular,
if I take expected value of both sides
of this expression, I get expected value
of YT for martingales is always equal to
expected value of YS.
So, that's a necessary condition for a
process to be a martingale. So, now I can
easily find the expected value, I wish.
I will use the property of a martingale.
So, I will say, that expected value of YT
is equal to expected value, and here
I may use any value of SS equal to 1S,
equal to 2S, equal to zero. Let's use the
value 0. Okay, the expected value of Y0.
That's guaranteed because YT is a
martingale.
Okay, but Y0 is exponent of alpha times
0 minus alpha square root over 2 times 0,
and it's 1.
That's a constant.
Okay, so, expected value of exponent of
alpha YT
minus alpha squared over 2T,
is equal to 1, because expected value of
a constant is a constant.
And then I just
factor the exponential into a product of
two of two terms expected value of
exponent of alpha YT times exponent of
minus alpha squared over 2 times D.
The second quantity is non-random, this
one is non-random.
And I can take it out of the integral.
And, finally, I get, that
expected value of exponent of alpha WT
is, we need to divide one by
exponent of minus Alpha squared over
2 times t.
And,
it is equal,
let's write our final answer exponent of
alpha squared over 2 times D.
So, we have used a very interesting trick,
we have transformed our process into a
martingale, and then it's easy to
calculate expected values for
martingales and using expected values
for martingales. We have recovered
expected value of an expression, that was
not a martingale.