[Music]
In this video we will find the formula for the price
of a call option.
We will start with the definition of a
call and put options. Then we will find
the put call option parity.
And then, finally, we will find the price
of a call option.
Okay, the call option gives you a right to buy
one share at a specified strike price K on a specified date t.
And the put option gives you on the
contrary a right to sell one share at a
specified strike price K on a specified
date T. In mathematical terms, that means,
that CT, the payoff, that the call option gives
you, is equal to St minus K, if St is
bigger than K, because, if St the share
price is bigger than K,
you will use your right to buy cheap to
buy at the price K. And you will
immediately sell the share and the
prices T, and your profit will be, as T
minus K. If the share price is too low,
you will not use your right to buy a
share at a specified strike price key.
And by the same logic, the price of
a put option at time moment big T PT is
equal to K minus St, if St is lower than
K. In this case you have incentives to
use your right. But if St is bigger than
K, you will not use your right to sell
one share, and your profit P big T will be zero.
Okay, let's look at this formulas for
CT and for PT, and let's subtract PT
from CT. We get CT minus PT is St minus K.
In any possible state of the world if St
is bigger than K, if St is lower than
K, this difference is St minus K.
So, the difference CT minus PT can be
simulated, replicated by holding one
share St. To have St at the end of time,
you can just buy one share in the beginning of time.
And the K at the end of time are
equivalent to K rubbles multiplied by exponent
of minus RT rubbles now. So, we have
proven, that C0 minus P0 is equal to S0
minus discounted K exponent minus RT
times K.
Now let's move on to the call option price.
We have two knight ducks with us, we call
the derivation is very difficult.
Okay, so, from the general pricing rule we have
that C0 is discounted exponent minus RT
discounted expected value star of, or
CT given F0.
But we know the formula for CT, we will
just rewrite it, using indicator I, that
is equal to 1, when St is bigger than K,
and it's equal to 0 otherwise. So, CT is
just I times CT minus K. We open the
brackets, it's I  times CT minus I times K.
And  the conditional expected value, even if
conditional expected value star is
linear. So, we will calculate the expected
value star of I times St minus
conditional expected value star of I times k.
Okay, let's  first start with the second
term. Why not?
Expected value star of I times K is
constant, we move it out of the
expected value, it's K times expected
value star of I given our information,
described by sigma algebra of zero, but
the indicator is either one or zero. So,
the expected value of the indicator is a
probability, that it will be equal to 1.
So, its probability star that St is
bigger than K.
Let's go down to WT star, the event St
In other terms it's logarithm of St
bigger, than logarithm of K.
Or logarithm of S0 plus R minus
sigma square root of 2 times T plus
sigma Wt star bigger than logarithm of K.
Or in terms of WT star we have Wt star
bigger than this fraction.
We will standardize WD star, so we
subtract 0, the expected value star of WT star we
divide by square root of variance by square root of T.
And we reverse the inequality, and we get
the event St bigger than K, is
equivalent to the event at minus Wt
star divided by square root of T, is less
than a constant D. The previous fraction
additionally divided by square root of T.
And here in the left side 0 minus WD
star divided by square root of T has
normal distribution 0 1. So, this
probability can be calculated it's
called cumulative distribution function.
We have done one half of the job. So,
expected value star of I times K given
information F0 is K times
probability star, that St is bigger than
K. Or K times normal cumulative distribution function
at the point D, where D is this fraction
Ln is 0 minus Ln K plus R minus sigma
squared over 2 times T divided by sigma
times square root of T.
Okay, let's move on to the final answer.
The first term: it's expected value star
of I times St. We plug in the value of
St, it's a 0 times exponent.
We plug in our indicator. That's an
indicator of WT star is less than D
times square root of T.
And now we have only Wiener process
inside our expected value. This expected
value we have in the tables and, so,
basically, we obtain our final answer for
the first term, as 0 is normal a standard
cumulative distribution function at the
point D plus sigma square root of T.
And we have the famous call option price
formula. C0 is equal to exponent minus RT
the discounting factor times brackets.
The first term is S0 multiplied by
normal distribution function at the
point D Plus Sigma square root of T
minus the second term K strike price
multiplied by normal distribution,
cumulative distribution function at the
point D, where D is a fraction logarithm
of a zero minus logarithm of K plus R
minus sigma square root over 2 times T
divided by sigma square root of T. Bingo!
Let's proceed to the summary. Call option
is right to buy one share, put option is
the right to sell one share.
Put call parity between the prices is C0
minus P0 equals to S0 minus discounted
strike price K.
and the call option price formula is
here. C0 is discounted sum of two terms:
the first term is S0 times cumulative
standard normal distribution function
minus K times the standard normal
distribution function at another point.
In the first term we use the point G
plus sigma times square root of T, in the
second term the cumulative distribution
function is evaluated at the point D.
We have obtained the famous Black and Scholes call option price formula.
[Music]