[Music]
In this video we will discuss a wide useful class of
random processes martingales.
We will use martingales to price assets
claims in the framework of Black
and Scholes models, but let's start first
with the filtration. Filtration is a
concept to model information acquisition.
Then we will define a martingale, and
then we will provide some examples of
martingales.
Okay, what a filtration is? The sigma
algebra FT describes all the information
available at time T, and if an agent is
rational, if he has a perfect memory, then,
his knowledge grows in time. So, that's a
formal definition of a filtration. The
family of sigma algebras FT indexed by a
time variable T is called filtration, if
it grows in time. So, basically FS is a
subset of FT for S less or equal to T. I
just remind you, that sigma algebra FT is
a collection of events.
What is a natural filtration? If you have
a process. If you observe, for example, a
process XT, and all you know
is the past values of XT, then your
knowledge is called natural filtration.
So, basically, natural filtration of a
process
describes the information of rational
agent, who knows past value of the
process. So, FT is generated by all random
variables XU for U from 0 to T.
Let's consider an example
of a Wiener process and its natural
filtration FT. One example: the event W2
is less, than 5 belongs to sigma algebra
F2, because at time moment 2, you know the
value of W2, and you know, whether it's
greater than 5 or less than 5.
The event W2 is greater than W5. This
event you know it at time moment 6,
whether this event has happened or not
happened, so, this event belongs to the
sigma algebra F6.
But, for example, if you can see the the
event W2 is less than 5, this event
does not belong to the list to the sigma
algebra F1, because  at time moment 1
you don't know, whether  W2 is less
that 5. And in  a similar fashion
W2 greater than W5 this, is that event
does not belong to the sigma algebra F2,
because at time moment 2 you don't have
enough information to decide, whether
this event has happened or not happened.
Now we are ready to define a martingale.
We can see the filtration FT a process
MT.
And if the best prediction of the future
value of a process MT is its current
value MS.
So, expected value of MT given sigma
algebra FS is MS, then MT is called a
martingale with respect to the
filtration FT.
So, what does this mean? This means, that,
basically, future changes are zero on
average. So, if I'm trying to predict the
future value of a process,
then the best prediction is its current
value, and so, I predict future
changes as zero. And usually we consider
a natural filtration FT of a process
MT.
Let's consider first very simple example
a constant process. If MT is always
777, that's the best forecast for future
value of MT given current information
is
777, so its current value.
Or another important example for us is a
Wiener process.
The best forecast of WT given current
information FS, I remind you that S is
before T.
I decompose future value WT, as current
value WS plus change.
Then I use the fact, that WS is known at
time moment test, so, I move it out of the
expected value. But future change WT
minus WS
is independent of FS. So, I remove a
conditional expected, I remove
information. And, conditional expected
value is equal to the unconditional one
and, hence, I get WS.
Let's consider one more example: ZT that
is equal to WT squared minus T is also a
martingale with respect to the natural
filtration of Wiener process. Let's check
this. We calculate expected value of
future value of the process, given
current information FS. So, time moment S
is before time moment T.
Once again we use the same trick as
always: with a compose future value WT as
a WS current value plus change WT minus
WS. Then we open
the A plus B squared, as A squared plus B
squared plus 2 times A times B.
T is a deterministic variable, so we move
it out of the expected value. And we
simplify. Basically, for simplification we
use
the two ideas: the first idea, that WS is
known at time moment S. So, we move it out
of the expected value like T.
And the second idea:
future change WT minus WS, or the
square root value of WT minus WS is
independent of current information FS, so
we emit our information sigma algebra FS.
And then, the last step:
we use the fact that WT minus WS has
normal distribution which means zero and
variance T minus S. So, we get the final
answer WS squared plus T minus S minus T
or WS squared minus S, that is ZS, so, the
process that T we are discussing is
indeed a martingale. One more example of
a martingale is a process ZT, that is
exponent of a times WT minus a squared T
over 2. This is a martingale for every
possible value of a constant A, and this
martingale is extremely useful in
pricing
financial claims in the Black and
Scholes model.
The concept of a martingale also works
in discrete time. So, imagine a filtration
FT, T now is a natural number zero, one,
two and so on. And the process MT  is
also defined for natural values of T
like 0, 1, 2 and so on.
And in discrete time, instead of checking,
that expected value of any future MT,
given current information FS is equal to
current value of S. This condition is
equivalent to a much simpler condition,
that expected value of the next value of
the process of MT plus 1, given a
current information FT is current value
empty.
So, it's much easier to check, that the
process is a martingale in discrete time
then in continuous time.
And for example, we will consider a very
famous process, that is called random
walk.
So, we have a sequence of identically
distributed and independent random
variables set: 1, Z2, Z3, and so on with
expected value of each random variable
equal to zero.
And if we calculate cumulative sum of
these variables. So, ST is Z1 plus A2,
plus ZT with initial value, as 0
equal to zero.
This process is called a random walk, and
the random walk is a martingale.
Let's describe our information: FT at
time moment T, we know, that one the two,
that three and so on ZT.
And if we will calculate expected value
of future ST, plus 1 given current
information FT. Then, we decompose ST
plus 1, as St plus change the T plus one
always the same logic future value is
current value plus change.
Then ST is known at time moment T. We
have enough information in sigma algebra
FT to calculate ST. So, we move it out of
the expected value.
And ZT plus 1 is independent of sigma
algebra FT, hence, when calculating
conditional expected value of ZT plus
one we are just calculating ordinary
unconditional expected value of the T
plus one and ordinary expected value of
ZT plus 1 is 0. So, we get SG and the
random walk is a martingale.
Let's recap: filtration or a sequence of
sigma algebras models the process of
information acquisition.
We have defined the concept of a
martingale. A Martingale is a very
special type of stochastic process, where
the best guess of future value of the
process is its current value.
And we have provided some examples
related to a WIener process.
[Music]