[Music]
Let's consider the properties of a
stochastic integral. We consider the
stochastic integral from 0 to TW power
4 times U times dWu. We know, that any
stochastic integral under some mild
conditions is a martingale with zero
expected value. So, the first question is
just is it like a cake. The expected
value of Ip is just zero. We are happy.
Now for the variance.
Let's use Ito isometry now. Let's say, that
variance of IT is expected value of IT,
and can be calculated, as ordinary bream
and integral. Integral from 0 to T.
We put
the expected value of square inside.
So, we calculate expected value of Wu
power 8 times U squared. And we change dWu
by just ordinary DU. Okay, that's
simple to calculate. We recall, that  WU
has the same distribution, as a square
root of U times Z, where Z is a standard
normal random variable. And the
expected value of Z power 8 is 7 times 5
times 3 times 1, that is a double
factorial.
And, hence, our expected value is almost
found. So, we get integral from 0 to T
expected value of square root of U
power 8 times Z power 8 times U squared
DU. We get
integral from 0 to T
U power 4
times U power 2 times 7 times 5 times 3
DU.
We got
integral from 0 to T
or 105 times U power 6 DU.
And, finally, we get 105 times U to the
power 7 divided by 7 U changes from zero
to T. And we get
times
T power 7.
And that's all.
Okay, we have calculated variance. Now
let's move on to covariance.
We need to calculate covariance of our
integral with  double UT squared.
Our main idea is the following: it's easy
to calculate, using Ito isometry the
covariance between integrals. So, it's
better to represent WT squared, as an
integral, because IT is already an
integral
of Wu power 4 times UDWU. So, it's
better to represent WT squared, as an
integral. How we may represent WT
squared, as an integral?
We may say, that it's WT squared minus t,
that is from our integral tables plus T,
and, so, we get, that this is basically
integral from 0 to T2 times WUDWU plus t.
Hence, we plug in both these integrals
into covariance. So, we have covariance of
integral from 0 to TWU power 4 times U
dWu with integral from 0 to T to
WUDW U plus t.
This plus T is a non-random quality. It
does not influence the covariance, so, we
just get rid of this T.
We need to calculate covariance
between two integrals. And covariance
between two integrals is just original
integral from 0 to T expected value of
the product of expressions inside
integrals. So, we need to multiply these
values,
and to take expected value of the
product.
So, we have here WU power 4 times U
times 2 WU.
And we use ordinary ariemann integral by
Ito  isometry.
We get UN2 out of expected value out
of integral.  2U integral from 0 to
T expected value of WU power 5 times DU.
This is odd power of Wu.
So, the expected value of odd power of
scaled standard normal random variable
is just zero. So, we got zero covariance.
And finally, let's calculate our
conditional expected value. Let's
calculate conditional expected value of
I6 given I4.
We use the property of stochastic
integral, that stochastic integral is a
martingale.
And, hence, the last question is also easy,
as it's a martingale, the best prediction
of its future value, if you know
current value is the current value.
So, it's I4, and it's integral from 0 to 4
Wu
power 4 times U times dWu.
Unfortunately, the explicit value of
stochastic integral can be calculated in
general, only in some rare cases we can
get the stochastic integral explicitly
without the integral sign.
[Music]