[Music]
In this video we will introduce Black and Scholes model. First, we will discuss the
assumptions of the model. Next, we will
move on to the main question.
And, finally, we will solve our first
stochastic differential equation, that
describes the price of a share.
Okay,
in the Black and Scholes model unique shape
type is traded.
And the share price satisfies the
following stochastic differential
equation: DST is equal to USD times DT
plus sigma ST times DWT. What does it
mean intuitively? If we consider a small
increment of time, then the change of
share price DST
is a sum of two terms. One roughly
non-stochastic muST times DT plus, the
second one is statistic: sigma times ST
times DWT.
And the risk-free interest rate are in
the Black and Scholes model is constant,
and unique for all horizons for one
month, for two months is for one year, for
five seconds is the same.
There are no taxes, no dividends, no
transactions costs in the
Black and Scholes model. Time is continuous, and
shares are infinitely divisible: you can
buy zero, zero, zero, zero one share.
And short selling is about you can sell
-5 assets.
And there are no arbitrage opportunities.
So, that means you cannot make profit
without risk.
And these parameters mu sigma R, they
are known constants.
The main question we would like to
answer is - how to calculate the price of
such or that financial claim?
So, for example, at time moment T equal to
2 John would like to get 10
rubels, if the price S2 is greater than
100 and nothing otherwise.
How much he should pay now?
That is the question.
And let's start solving the
Black and Scholes model, and answering  the
main question by solving the stochastic
differential equation for the price. It
is DST equal to Mu St plus times DT plus
sigma ST times DWT.
Or in full form with integrals
STS0 plus Riemann integral USUDU
plus stochastic integral sigma SU dWu.
Let's focus once again on the short form,
because it's a little bit easier to work
with. So, DST is UST times DT plus sigma ST
times DWT.
And let's recall our mnemonic rules, and
let's calculate DST squared with
mnemonic rules. So, it is Mu ST times DT
plus sigma S T D W T squared. DT times DT
is 0. DT times DWT is 0. And DWT times DWT
is DT. We open the brackets, and we
get sigma squared times ST squared
times DT. Okay, now let's consider the log
of ST. The process YT is just a logarithm
a natural logarithm of ST. According to
Ito's lemma, dYt is equal to the first
derivative with respect to S times DS
plus the first derivative with respect
to T times DT, but there are no T in
logarithm of S, and the derivative of
logarithm of S is one over S.
And in the Ito's lemma we have a second
derivative with respect to S multiplied
by 1 over 2, the second derivative is
minus 1 of S squared.And we multiply it
by DS squared, and we already have the
expression for DS squared, that was
calculated one Step before. And, hence, we
get the expression for dYt. dYt is Mu
DT plus sigma tWt minus sigma squared
over 2 times DT.
Hmm, that's great! we have the equation
for logarithm of share price in a short
form. dyt equals some constant times DT
plus sigma times DWT. We go to the full
form.
And in the full form we have two easy
integrals. We have YT is equal to Y0
plus Riemann integral of a constant
times DU plus Ito's integral sigma
times DW. We can calculate these
integrals. And we get logarithm of ST is
equal to logarithm of S0, because it's
the value of Y0 plus mu minus sigma
squared over 2 times T plus sigma times
DWT. And, as we have an expression for
logs, then we go to the expression for S.
Finally, ST is equal to S0 times exponent
of Mu minus sigma squared over 2
times T plus sigma times WT. And we see,
that in the Black and Scholes model the
price of a share follows the geometric
Browonial motion.
Let's make a small summary.
The main goal of the Black and Scholes model
is to calculate the price of such
of that financial claim.
The share price follows the geometric
Brownian motion. So, ST
is equal to S0 times exponent of Mu
minus sigma squared, so, into Times T plus
sigma times WT.
Risk-free rate is assumed constant. And I
should point out, that there are no
arbitrage opportunities in the Black and Scholes model,
you cannot make risk-free
profit, you should risk to make profit.