[Music]
In this video we will introduce Girsanov theorem. First, we will start with appealing, but
wrong answer to the pricing problem.
Then we will introduce the idea of
alternative probability and then, finally,
we will state the Girsanov theorem.
First, let's provide the wrong intuition.
It seems, that the future payoff XT is
random. And to calculate the current
price of something, that is random in the
future, we just need to calculate the
expected payoff given current
information. So, it seems at first a
glance, that X0 should be equal to
expected value of Xt given initial
information F0.
But this intuitive idea is wrong.
It will be true for a martingale, but the
claim price
Xt is not a martingale.
So, that's the main idea, why this answer
is wrong.
We will modify it to make it correct.
First, let's introduce the idea of
alternative probability. Normally in
probability of statistics we work with
just one probability. There is only one
true probability P.
In the Black and Scholes model it's very
useful to introduce alternative
probability P star. So, we will have two
probabilities: probability P and
probability P star. Imagine the following.
A simple example: the random variable X
takes three values either minus two,
either zero, either four. And we have
probability P.
The probability P, that X is equal to
minus 2 is 0 3, but the probability P
star, that X is equal to -2 is 0 4. So,
they are different.
And we can calculate different expected
values.
For example, expected value of X is 0 6.
You just multiply value by probability
and you add. And the expected value star,
the expected value calculating, using
alternative probability is different, is
one over two, because the probability is
different. So, we will work with two
probabilities now. And we need to pay
attention: there will be expected value
and expected value star, and they will be
different.
The main reason to introduce the
new probability P star in the Black and
Scholes model is to simplify the
calculation of prices.
And, finally, we are ready to state the
Girsanov theorem. If Wt is a Wienner process
and the probability P, and WT star is a
Brownian motion with drift, that means it
is equal to B times t plus Wt. Then there
is a probability P star such, that Wt
star is a Wiener process on the P star.
So, that means sWt is a Wiener process,
it's expected value is zero.
And expected value of Wt star, because we
add B times T inside expected value. So,
we get B times T, but if I change
probability, if I change expected value
to expected value star, I will get
expected value star of W star is zero,
because under probability measure P star
W star is once again a Wiener process.
We can state Girsanov theorem applied
specially for Black and Scholes model. And
the Black and Scholes model, there is an
alternative probability P star such, that
Wt star is a Wiener process on the P
star. And St is equal to S0 times
exponent of R
minus sigma squared over 2 times T
plus sigma times Wt star.
The old formula is still valid as T is
as 0 times exponent
mu minus sigma squared over 2 plus
sigma times Wt. Where Wt is a Wiener
process and the probability P. So, both
forms are okay.
Let's find a link between Wt and Wt star.
As formulas equivalent we can derive,
that mu minus sigma squared of 2
times T plus sigma times Wt is equal to
R minus sigma squared over 2 times T
plus sigma Wt star. We simplify a little
bit. We can get rid of sigma squared
over 2. And we get, that mu minus R times
T plus sigma times Wt, Wt is the Wiener
process on the P is equal to sigma times
Wd star, that is a Wiener process under
probability P star. Or we may write the
same equation in a short form, we just
add D everywhere, so, we have mu minus R
times Dt plus sigma times dWt is equal
to sigma times dWt star.
The meaning of probabilities is the
following P is a real world probability.
It determines, how the future will happen.
And P star is an artificial probability,
that is used to simplify formulas.
We have seen, that big expression with
dWt is equivalent to a small expression
with WT star, and that's the reason to
introduce the probability measure P star.
Let's make a small summary.
First point fair price of a financial
claim is not a simple expected value,
it's a little bit more difficult to
calculate.
And Girsanov theorem gives two equivalent
formulas for St. St is a zero times
exponent R minus sigma squared of 2
times T plus sigma times Wt star. Or the
same expression with R replaced by mu
and the sigma, and the WT star by WT.
And, once again, Wd star is a Wiener
process on the artificial probability P
star. And the big expression mu minus R
Dt plus sigma dWt is a very small
sigma times dWt star in this mu terms.
So, basically, that's the reason to
introduce new probability measure to
simplify X position.