[Music]
In this video we will simulate the trajectory of it, as
integral.
We will use the functions to create the
trajectory of Wiener process, that we
have studied a last lecture.
And then, let's start with Ito integral.
Okay, so, we will create the function get
in the ground trajectory.
Trajectory and this function will use D,
the final moment of time and the number of small intervals.
1000 by default the seed. The initial
value for random number generation.
And let's go. Okay, first, we will create
deltas increments of Wiener process. We
will calculate the values of integrand,
we will multiply deltas increments of
Wiener process by the values of integral,
and We will integral, and then we will sum
up these products.
Okay, deltas or increments of Wiener
process may have already made function.
Get Wiener increments
T is equal to T, and is equal to N.
Seed is equal to seed.
Okay, we got deltas of Wiener
process. Next we create the Wiener
process, we create a vector of zeros
first of size N plus 1, because we have
N intervals and N plus 1 time moments.
Then we say, that values of W from 1 to N
plus 1 are just cumulative sums
of increments of Wiener process.
Then we create time moments.
We get time T equal to TN equal to N.
Then we calculate our integrand.
Integrand will be
in our case, that is just  W power 3.
These are the values of the integrand.
And then we calculate, basically, the
integrand times delta
or this is delta of integral.
We just multiply
integrands value in 10 round values from
0 to N. The last one is not used, because
we have no future increments for the
last value of the integrand.
And we just multiply it one by one, by
delta of Wiener process.
And we sum up these values.
We say, that in integral
is a vector of zeros big Vector of zeros
of size N plus 1.
And like with Wiener process, we
copy the same logic,
but we apply it to our integral
trajectory. It will be accumulative sum
of increments of the integral of delta's
integral.
Okay, and we return
our integral trajectory.
We have created
our function. Let's check it.
Let T be equal to 2, let N be equal to
one thousand. Let's get
time moments for this T, and for this
N. Let's get the integral trajectory
for this T for this N.
And let's plot it SNS line plot.
X will be just our T.
And Y will be the values of our integral.
And we see that the time evolution of
our stochastic integral is quite
different from the evolution of the
Wiener process itself. It stays near zero
a long time, we may simulate it more.
And that's another trajectory.
And we may also study the properties of
this stochastic integral empirically.
Let's do this. Now let's calculate the
variance of
this stochastic integral at time moment
three. So, let's calculate the variance of
I3.
To do this, we will simulate many
trajectories. We will say, that we will
simulate
10 000 trajectories. Final moment of time
will be three.
We will subdivide our time interval from
0 to 3 into 1 000
small time intervals.
And we will keep a record of all final
values of our stochastic integral
trajectory. So, we will say final value,
that will be a vector. We will reserve a
little bit of memory.
We will say, that we need the number
of simulations a vector with this number
of zeros will be reserved. And then we
launch a cycle.
We say, that for I ranging from 0 to N
minus 1, so, and sigma and C
for I in. Sorry, I miss thing.
And then what should we create? We should
create the whole trajectory, get the last
value of that trajectory and keep it in
memory. And then we will calculate the
sample variance, that will be close and
closer to the true variance. Well, when we
will increase the number of simulations.
Okay, so, integral trajectory
will be get in the
moral trajectory
for
T equal to TN equal to N.
And we will keep track of the last value.
So, final value
number, it will be integral
trajectory
number N,
the last value.
So, we launch the cycle, we wait a little
bit.
And then we have a big vector of final
values. Let's see
the beginning of it.
For example, first 10 values.
These are first 10 values of our
experiments. And we basically calculate
the standard deviation.
So, we just say numpy variance of this
big vector.
And we got this estimate of the true
variance. Obviously, that's only an
estimate. And to check, whether the
estimation is precise or not, we may
relaunch our set of simulations
and see, whether the answer is stable.
And we see, that it's more or less stable
it's 270 something.
So, obviously, if we will produce, if we
will use a higher number of simulations
and higher number of sub intervals, we
will get the result, that is more and
more, and more precise, but for
infinite number of simulations and
infinite number of  small time
segments, we will need infinite amount of time.
[Music]