[Music]
Our course is about problem solving, so, let's solve
some problems. Let's calculate expected
value variance and covariance. let's
calculate expected variance of T times
WT, where WT is a Wiener process power
four. Okay. As t is non-random, we just take
it out.
And is T expected value of WT power 4.
Next we will standardize our random
variable WT power 4. So, we use the fact
that
WT has the same distribution, as square
root of T times standard  random,
variable normal standard print, variable
Z.
And if I will do this
substitution, the distribution will not
change and the expected value will not
change. So, I will get T times expected
value of square root T times Z power 4.
As T is non-random, I will take squared
T squared out of the brackets. That's T
times T squared times expected value of
Z power 4. Now I see that that power 4
is a power of a standard normal random
variable, so I can use the effect which
can be established, using integration or
some other tricks. That expected value of
ZN.
For even N is N minus 1, times N minus 3,
times N minus all.
Odd numbers Q1. In my case it will be
T cube times 4 minus 1 is 3. I
subtract two more is one, and voila.
So we get 3 times T cubed.
Now let's move on to the calculation of
variance.
We need to calculate variance of T times
WT power 4 plus T squared. First, we use
the property of variance that we can add
constants non-random quantities for free.
So we just get variance of T times WT
power 4 plus nothing. Okay, we take out T,
but now with square.
We get T squared times variance of WT
power 4.
Now  we will do once again the same
substitution, we will say that WT has the
same distribution as square root of T
times some standard normal random
variable. And hence using this
substitution, we get tT squared times
variance of square root of T times Z
power 4.
That is equal.
Now I have  T squared inside brackets,
but it will go out with one more square.
So, I get T squared times T squared
squared times variance of that
power 4.
And I get T power 6.
And now I get expected value of Z power
8 minus expected value of Z power 4
squared. I have used the definition of
variance. And then I get T power 6
and I use the moment formula for normal
standard random variable. And hence, I
have 7 times 5 times 3 times 1 minus
three times one
squared.
And finally, I get T power 6 times
seven times three, it will be 21, 105
minus 9.
And hence, we have calculated variance.
And now let's move to covariance.
Usually we will consider two moments
of time SNT and for simplicity we will
make an agreement that S is less than T.
Let's calculate covariance.
Covariance of T times WT with WS squared
is equal. According to the definition of
covariance, it's expected value of the
product T times, WT times, WS squared
minus
the product of  expected value.
Expected value of T times WT times
expected value of WS squared.
Okay.
First, let's make some simple remarks.
Here we can move T outside. And expected
value of WT is zero, so we will ignore
the second term. And let's focus on
the first one. Here we move T once again
out of the brackets. And we get T
times expected value of WT times WS
squared.
And here we have  two correlated  or
probably dependent variables.
And we need to be careful here,
because these variables,
they may be dependent.
And so let's use our standard trick. We
will represent future value, as past
value plus some  unpredictable
independent increment. So, we will replace
WT with past value WS plus independent
increment. So, plus WT minus WS that is it
future value.
This is plus value
plus increment.
That's our standard trick.
Let's see what we will have. We will have
T times expected value of Ws plus Wt
minus Ws
times Ws squared.
We are almost done. We have T times
expected value of Ws cubed.
That is 0, because it's a odd moment of
scaled standard normal random
variable.
Plus T times expected value of
WT minus Ws times Ws squared. And hence
we. Here we know that WT minus Ws and
WS are independent.
Here we have independency. So, we may
decompose our expected value into a
product of expected values.
So, we have a T times expected value of
WT minus WS times expected value of WS
squared.
From the definition of Wiener process of
Brownian motion, we know that WT minus WS
has normal distribution with mean 0 and
variance T minus S. And hence, this
expected value is 0, because of the first
term.
And even more, let's calculate some easy
probability. Let's calculate probability
of
3 times W 4 minus W 3 greater than zero.
Let's calculate this probability.
As we have a linear combination of
values of Wiener process, we know, that
this random variable has normal
distribution. So, this variable has normal
distribution with some mean
and some variance.
But what is the mean of this linear
combination expected value of 3 times W
4 minus W 3 is 3 times 0 minus 0 is 0.
And honestly speakingб I don't care about
the variance.
I have the probability that
normal distribution with mean 0 and some
variance is greater than zero.
Soб it's probability that some normal
variable with mean 0 and some variance
is greater than zero, but due to the
symmetry of this normal variable around
zero, I get one point.
One over two
[Music]