[Music]
Let's work with martingales, because
martingales are very powerful  in
option pricing. So, let's start working
with them.
Okay, let's consider the process XT, which
is equal to 6 times WT squared plus
alpha T. And we know, that XT is a
martingale, so, on average it is not going
up, it's not going down.
And our goal is to find alpha, when
it's not specified we are working with
natural filtration, so, our information
available at time moment T is generated
by observing the Wiener process. So, we
know values WU for U from zero up to
time moment T.
So, basically, that means that the time
moment T we know WT and all previous W's.
Okay, what is the main property of
martingales. The main property of martingales,
that expected value of future XT,
given current information is current
value XS.
Okay, and let's find Alpha, that will
solve this equation. So, we will calculate
left hand side and make it equal to the
right hand side.
Okay, what is the expected value of 6 WT
squared plus Alpha T given FS.
Once again, we will use our trick we will
decompose future value into past value
plus independent increment. Let's do it.
We have alpha T is a non-random quality,
quantity we move it out of the expected
value.
And we get inside expected value
T squared given FS. Now
our tricks is in play. We replace
WT, as WS known value plus future
increment WT minus WS squared given FS.
Let's continue.
We get alpha T plus 6 times,
we open the brackets and we will get WS
squared plus 2 times WS plus increment
WT, minus WS, plus increment squared
WT, minus WS squared given FS.
Now
We see, that we have terms of two types:
WS is known,
is fixed at time
moment S,
and increment
is independent
of what we know.
So, basically, these are two main cases we
work with every time.
So, we get alpha T plus six.
WS squared is known, so, the best
prediction the X conditional expected
value is Ws squared. Plus it is fixed, so,
we can move it out, it looks like a
constant for us. So, we have WS
conditional expected value of WT minus
WS even that we know FS plus conditional
expected value of WT, minus WS
squared, if we know FS.
We continue.
We see, that this increment is
independent of what we know,
and, hence, we replace conditional
expected value by unconditional one. We
get alpha T plus six WS squared, plus 12
WS times unconditional expected value
of WG, minus WS, plus unconditional
expected value of WT, minus WS squared.
Okay, we know from the definition of
Wiener process, that WT minus WS has
normal distribution with means zero and
variance T minus S.
Hence, this is zero,
and this is exactly
the variance of WT minus WS, and this is
T minus S.
So, we are almost done.
This is alpha T plus 6 times WS squared,
plus 12 times WS times 0 plus.
I forgot here six.
Plus six times T minus S.
Okay,
what do I have here. I have
6 WS squared
Plus
six plus Alpha times T
minus 6 S.
And what should I have to make XT a
martingale. To make XT a martingale, I
should have here 6 WS square root minus,
sorry, plus Alpha times s.
I should have no T there,
so, alpha should be equal to -6.
If Alpha is -6, I have no T,
and I have the perfect correspondence
with
XS.
So, we got the value of alpha. Now let's
move one egg and consider exponential
martingale or Wiener process, and let's
find out the value of beta.
Once again, we do our famous trick: we
decompose
future value into past value plus
increment. Let's do this first, and then
we will move on to the calculation of
expected value, we said, that it is 6 times
WS plus 6 times WT minus WS
plus beta T.
And we can factor this expression,
because plus inside exponent, that is,
basically, multiplication of different
exponents. So, we got exponent of 6 W S
times exponent of 6
increments,
times exponent of beta T.
Okay, and now let's recall the basic
equation for martingale, the basic
equation for martingale. The definition
the expected value of YT, given FS should
be YS. So, let's calculate left hand side,
and let's choose  beta to make left
hand side equal to the right hand side.
Okay.
So, expected value of exponent of 6 W S
times exponent of six increments
WT minus WS times
exponent of beta times T,
given
FS.
This is a
fixed value, this is fixed value, so, I
move them out of the expectation,
and I will get
exponent of 6 W S times exponent of beta
T times.
And now I have the expected value of
some function of increment, so my
information is useless, because future
increment is independent of the past
value
of Wiener process, so, I replace this by
unconditional expectation of 6 WT
minus WS.
Now let's look at the moment generating
function of a standard normal random
variable. If Z is a standard normal
random variable, then its moment
generating function or expectation of
exponent of U times Z is equal by
exponent of U squared over 2. So, in my
case where is that, but I know that here,
but I may easily introduce it. I know,
that
the WT minus WS has exactly the same
distribution, as square root of T minus S
times Z, because left and right hand
sides they both have a normal
distribution
with mean 0 and variance T minus S.
So, I may just think of this increment or,
as
a square root of T minus S times Z. Okay,
so,  I need to calculate expected value
of exponent of 6 times square root of T
minus S times Z.
And according to the moment generating
function,
that will be exponent of 36 times T
minus S over 2.
Bingo! We are almost done. So, we have
exponent of 6 W S plus beta T
plus  18
times T minus S.
Okay, let's simplify this a little bit.
And we get
exponent of 6 W S
plus T times
beta plus 18
minus 18 S.
And to make YT is a martingale, we
should get YS
in the right hand side.
So, we should get what is YS. This is the
definition of YT, and to get YS, we
need to have exponent of 6 W S
plus
beta times S.
We should have no T in this expression,
and, so, to cancel out T, and to get beta S
or minus 18, as the only beta, that is
okay, it is beta
equal to minus 18, because with this
value of beta T will cancel out,
and beta S will be exactly minus 18S. So,
we have solve our two problems. We
know, that the first process XT is a
martingale for alpha equal minus 6. And
the second process YT is a martingale
for beta equal to minus 18.
So, we're happy, we have found two
martingales. And martingales will be very
useful in calculating prices of
options in Black and Scholes model.
[Music]