[Music]
Let's consider one more no-arbitrage
pricing problem. We work in a setup of
Black and Scholes model. We assume, that S0,
the starting price of a share, is ten
dollars. Risk-free interest rate is 0.05
And sigma is 0 1 the volatility.
Okay, and let's consider a very, very
strange asset, very strange asset X. At
time moment 2 this strange asset pays
you X2 cube, S2 cube.
If S2 will be 10, you will receive one
thousand. If S2 will be one, you will
receive one. If S2 will be 5, you will
receive 125 dollars. That's a very
strange asset. And let's price it.
There is a unique no-arbitrage price
in the framework of Black and Scholes model.
This is current price X0, and let's
find it out.
First, let's do some simple remarks: that
if I have one dollar in future, this
future dollar now is priced less
than one. And it's actual price is
exponent of minus 2 times R, because I
need to discount this future dollar to
current prices. And one share in the
future is just one share at the start is 10.
Okay, so let's price our strange asset X.
We have a theorem: that's under some nice
probability measure, discounted price
is a martingale. So, martingales, they
make our life easier. So, this theorem
says, that's very easy to calculate X0,
it's expected value.
Okay, we have, that X0
is an expected value, a strange expected
value, risk-free expected value
of discounted future payoff of our
contract. So, it is expected value star
risk-free expected value of discounted.
So, I need to write exponent of minus 2R
here times future or price of my asset X2.
And to make calculations easier, we
will express X2 in terms of risk-free
interest rate. Okay, what is X2?
X2 is just S 2 Cube. And what is S2? In the black
And Scholes model it is S0 times exponent.
And here I may write two possible
expressions for St, but I will use the
expression with risk-free interest rate
R and start Brownian motion.
Okay, it will be R minus sigma square
root over 2 times future time moment 2 plus sigma times W2 star.
And I need to calculate cube.
Okay, how do we calculate cube? We will
Ñube, as 0, and we just multiply by three
the expression inside exponent. So, we
will get X2 equals to S 0 cubed multiplied by exponent
of 6 times R minus sigma squared over 2 plus 3 sigma W2 star.
Okay, and now let's calculate its start expected value.
X0 is a start expected value of
exponent minus 2R times S0 cubed
times exponent of 6R minus 3 sigma
squared plus three sigma W2 star.
And I need to close the bracket for expected value.
Okay, I move a constants out of the
expected value. This is constant, this is
constant, this is like a constant,
and I get expect exponent of minus 2R times S0
cubed times exponent of 6 R minus 3 sigma squared,
multiplied by, what is left
expected value of star of exponent of 3
sigma W2 Star.
Okay, and what is this expected value?
We know, that we have even proven it with
martingales, that ordinary expected
value of exponent of
alpha times WT, is just exponent of alpha
squared times T over 2. And the same
holes of four started version of this
expression. So, expected value star, so,
expected value with respect to different
probability measure A of exponent of
alpha times Wt star, that's the same thing, because the
distribution of WT with respect to
probability measure P is the same, as the
distribution of WT star with respect
to probability measure P star. So, it's
just exactly the same value
Alpha scored T over 2.
And, hence, I can continue my calculations of X0.
I simplify a little bit, I see minus 2
here and 6 there. So, I will get
exponent of 4R minus 3 sigma squared times S0 cubed.
And this expected value. Now I need
just to find the alpha in this term.
And I get the exponent
of alpha squared 9 sigma squared times T.
T is 2 times 2 divided by 2.
And, finally, I get S0 cube times exponent of 4R.
Here I have minus 3 sigma squared,
here I have plus 9 sigma squared. So, I
have a plus 6 sigma squared. And that is a fair price.
The unique no-arbitrage price, let's copy it.
So, we have found, that X0 is just, as zero
cube times exponent of 4r plus 6 sigma square root.
And if we plug in our our values,
then we get, X0 is just 1000 multiplied by exponent
4 times, 0 0 5 is 0 2 times 0 0 6, it will
be 0 26. And we will get approximately 1296.9.
And voila!
We have found unique no-arbitrage price of this tricky asset.
[Music]